<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The compleat mother, or, An earnest perswasive to all mothers (especially those of rank and quality) to nurse their own children by Henry Newcome ...</title>
            <author>Newcome, Henry, 1650-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 113 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53076</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N893</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3355</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12268017</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12268017</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58129</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53076)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58129)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 156:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The compleat mother, or, An earnest perswasive to all mothers (especially those of rank and quality) to nurse their own children by Henry Newcome ...</title>
                  <author>Newcome, Henry, 1650-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 112 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Wyat ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. 112.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Breast feeding --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58129:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58129:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Compleat Mother. OR An Earneſt Perſwaſive to all Mothers (eſpecially thoſe of Rank and Quality) to Nurſe their own Children.</p>
            <q>
               <p>A partu ſtatim excipit lactandi cura. Atque hic quidem crat omni Machinarum genere pugna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum adverſus <hi>Pravam</hi> conſuetudinem, ſed mirum quam vulgo receptam, quà Matres Infantulos ſuos conductitiis mulieribus tradunt nutriendos.</p>
               <bibl>Eraſm. de Matrimonio Chriſtiano. p. 398.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Nil tam praeter Naturam, quam ut Mulier quod genuit, recuſet alere.</p>
               <bibl>Idem Eraſ. ibid.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Sine eam totam, integram eſſe Matrem ſui Filii.</q>
            <q>
               <p>Permit her to be the whole Compleat Mother of her Son.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>A. Gell. Noct. Att.</hi> l. 12. c. 1.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>By HENRY NEWCOME, A. M. and Rector of <hi>Tatten-hall</hi> in the County Palatine of <hi>Cheſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Wyat</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1695.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:58129:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Humf. Hody R. in Ch. P. ac D. D. Johanni Div. Provid. Archiep. Cant. à Sacris Dom.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aug. 18. 1694.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:58129:2"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>The Introduction.</label> THE Author's Motives to this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, <hi>viz. Compaſſion for Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> injured by being Nurſed by Strangers, <hi>Charity to ſuch Mothers</hi> as are reproach'd for doing their Duty, The Senſe of his own Obligations to oppoſe the Luxury of the Age: And hopes that ſuch a plain Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe may meet with ſome Succeſs. <hi>p. 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. I.</label> The Caſe is briefly ſtated, and all thoſe Texts of Scripture are alledged, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to it: Together with the Arguments and Inferences which reſult from them. <hi>p. 15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. II.</label> The great Miſchiefs which Mothers by transferring the Nurſing of their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to other Women, threaten <hi>their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies</hi> with both in point of <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> and that <hi>Mutual Affection</hi> which ought to be among the ſeveral Branches of it. <hi>p 47</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:58129:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. III.</label> The Inconveniencies reſulting to the <hi>Children themſelves</hi> which are Nurſed by Strangers, in reſpect of <hi>their Bodies,</hi> either through the <hi>Nurſes want of Care,</hi> the <hi>Unſuitable Nouriſhment,</hi> or <hi>Conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Diſeaſes</hi> tranſmitted in her Milk. <hi>62</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. IV.</label> The Miſchiefs which may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated from Mercenary Nurſes to the <hi>Minds</hi> of Children. <hi>p. 76</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. V.</label> The <hi>Common Plea's</hi> for Nurſing Children abroad: Together with the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency of them, and the True Cauſes thereof. <hi>p. 86</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>The Concluſion.</label> A Pathetick Addreſs to all, both <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Mothers,</hi> that they will admit the Preceding Particulars into their Serious and Impartial Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>p. 98</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="introduction">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58129:3"/>
               <head>THE INTRODUCTION.</head>
               <p>§ 1. CUſtom like an impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Torrent makes its way through the firmeſt Incloſures, and furiouſly throws down all the Bulworks of Laws, and the moſt Sacred Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations that obſtruct its paſſage. Like a mighty Tyrant it uſurps upon Truth and Duty, and awes all into a Compliance with its violent Government. Men live (as <hi>Seneca</hi> obſerves) not by <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> but by <hi>Imitation;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De beata vita. <hi>c. 1.</hi>
                  </note> whence it comes to paſs, that they fall upon one another by heaps, as ſo many Blind-men into a Ditch. It were eaſie to inſtance in many things, ſtrangely unreaſonable, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing recommended by Cuſtom, have paſſed not only without
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58129:4"/>Controle, but with Applauſe. I wiſh there were not too many <hi>popular Vices</hi> in our own Nation, to prevent the labour of ſuch an undertaking; Vices, which though they have nothing to juſtifie them beſides their Commonneſs, have even by that alone been able hitherto to baffle the moſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous Attempts againſt them. To mention no more, how many good Laws have been made, how many rational and elaborate Diſcourſes have been publiſhed both from the Pulpit and the Preſs againſt <hi>Common Swearings, Intemperate Drinking, Black-mouth'd Perjury</hi> and <hi>Bloody Revenge?</hi> And yet with little other effect hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, than to give us ſo many the more Inſtances of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs of <hi>Brutiſh Cuſtom</hi> over Reaſon and Religion: And to convince us that all ſuch At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts are as hopeleſs, as for <hi>one with ten thouſand,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 14.31.</note> 
                  <hi>to meet him that cometh againſt him with twenty
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58129:4"/>thouſand:</hi> Where the Aſſailant is more likely to be condemned for his <hi>Raſhneſs,</hi> than applauded for his <hi>Courage</hi> and <hi>Reſolution.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§ 2. It may then be juſtly wondred at, how I come to be ſo daring, as to oppoſe my weak Arms againſt ſuch a mighty Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, or to undertake the control<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Cuſtom, which hitherto hath prevailed againſt all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of Authority, Reaſon and Eloquence far greater than I can pretend to: This I mean of <hi>Mothers declining to Nurſe their own Children, and putting them off to Strangers. Annius Minutius</hi> the Roman Cenſor, is ſaid to have took notice of it as a ſtrange Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digy in his time, extreamly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minous to <hi>Rome,</hi> that a Roman Lady refuſing to Nurſe her own Child, gave Suck to a Puppy, that her Breaſts might with more ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be dried up by artificial Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations. But it is a thing too common, to paſs for a Prodigy
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58129:5"/>among us (though I fear not leſs fatally ominous) for Perſons of the beſt Quality to run the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Hazards, and ſubmit to the moſt unhandſom Methods for dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up their Suck, rather than to become Nurſes to their own Children. And I find a moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined Pen (than whom none in this Age could have been more likely to have ſucceeded,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ladies Calling,</hi> Part 2. Sect. 2. §. 28.</note> if either Reaſon, Eloquence, or a more charming ſtrain of extraordinary Piety be of any force) declining to attack this prevailing Cuſtom, through meer Deſpair of convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing by any thing that could be ſaid.</p>
               <p>§ 3. But upon mature Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, I can find no reaſon why Impudence and Obſtinacy ſhould protect any Sin from a juſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof: Nor can I think it a juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiable piece of Modeſty to decline the defence of a good Cauſe, meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the Multitude and Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of its Opponents. It was
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58129:5"/>brave in the Stripling <hi>David</hi> to aſſault the monſtrous Gyant with his Sling and a few Stones; and the Succeſs was anſwerable to his Courage. And why may not I (relying on the ſame God) hope for as good Succeſs from theſe my ſlender Endeavours, ſince the Cauſe I undertake, though it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the beſt, is ſufficient to give Victory to the meaneſt Advocate? Leaving therefore the Event to God's Providence, I am encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to aſſault this ſtubborn and inveterate Cuſtom.</p>
               <p n="1">1. By an hearty Compaſſion for the Infants which ſuffer by it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For a neceſſary Vindication of thoſe few honourable Ladies who have had the Vertue and Courage by their Practiſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And by the Senſe of my own Duty, as a Clergy-man, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear againſt the Luxury of the Age.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:58129:6"/>
               <p>§ 4. For the firſt: I am not aſhamed to own a peculiar Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation in my ſelf, to love and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the Converſation of little Children, among whom I have always found a moſt agreeable Diverſion. Nor need I, ſince our Bleſſed Lord himſelf gave encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to bring ſuch little ones to him, was pleaſed to take them in his Arms, and to propoſe their Innocence to our Imitation. And as this hath induced me to ſpend all my vacant Hours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Children for their Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement, as well as the gratify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of mine own Inclinations; ſo it makes me the more Impatient at all thoſe, who betray any Aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or are guilty of any Unkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs toward them. And ſince the Children of our Nobility and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try are juſtly reputed to be the Hopes of the next Generation, it is reaſonable to be moſt concern'd for them; who in their Infancy generally are more Unhappy than
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58129:6"/>the Sons of <hi>Country Peaſants.</hi> The <hi>Poor Tenants Child</hi> is for the moſt part nurſed in its <hi>own Mothers</hi> Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, and cheriſhed by her Breaſts, whilſt the <hi>Landlord's Heir</hi> is turn'd out, exil'd from his Mothers em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces as ſoon as from her Womb, and aſſigned to the Care of ſome Stranger, who hath no other En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dearments toward it, than what are owing ſolely to her Intereſt. And ſuch as work for Wages, are uſually not ſo careful how they do their Work, as to get their Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend; nor is a Mercinary Nurſe much concerned how the Infant Improves, provided ſhe have a good place of it. Thus the Infants of the beſt Families are moſt hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſed, and vaſt numbers of them <hi>undoubtedly deſtroyed.</hi> And ſure I need not deſpair of Pardon even from thoſe Ladies who are moſt concerned in the enſuing Reproof, ſince it is the reſult of my real and hearty Compaſſion for their dear Children.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:58129:7"/>
               <p>§ 5. Beſides Secondly, I have obſerved, that thoſe Ladies, who contrary to this prevailing Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, have undertaken the Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery of their own Babes, have oft met with unhandſom Reflections and bitter Taunts from others of the contrary Practiſe, which makes the Vindication of them a neceſſary piece both of Juſtice and Charity. A Lady that will condeſcend to be a Nurſe, though to her own Child, is become as Unfaſhionable and Ungenteel, as a Gentleman that will not Drink, Swear and be profane; but dares be out of Faſhion in leading an exactly vertuous and ſober Life. Apd if ever you ſaw the Modeſty of ſuch an one aſſaulted by the Railery and Scorn of a Company of Debauchees, when he happens to fall among them: You may imagine the need thoſe few La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies have of Courage and Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who by Nurſing their own Children, expoſe themſelves to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58129:7"/>the Taunts and Deriſion of <hi>the many,</hi> who decline that Office, and look upon themſelves to be upbraided by their Examples.</p>
               <p>§ 6. And when I obſerve thoſe few Ladies, who beſt diſcharge their Duties, expoſed to the Scoffs of ſuch as neglect theirs; and on the other hand, reflect on the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happineſs of thoſe poor Infants, whoſe Mothers make it a Pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctilio of State to caſt them off to the Care of Strangers, I cannot but believe it a good Office, and a few hours well beſtowed, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt the Vindication of the <hi>beſt Mothers,</hi> and to plead (with thoſe that are otherwiſe) the cauſe of thoſe helpleſs <hi>Innocents,</hi> who are not able, unleſs in their inarticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late cries, to ſpeak for themſelves. Eſpecially</p>
               <p>§ 7. Since thirdly, the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of my own Obligations, as a Clergyman, encourage me in this undertaking. For in the Book en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled,<note place="margin">Cap. 13. <hi>De Matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Reformatio Legum Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticarum,</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:58129:8"/>which was compoſed by eight Biſhops (whereof Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Cranmer</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Ridley</hi> were two) eight Divines, and as many Civil and Common Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, in purſuance of an Act of Parliament, and intended for the Government of the Reformed Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the Rules of Eccleſiaſtical Courts, I find this paſſage. <q>A Cuſtom too ſoft and delicate hath prevailed among Wives, to diſcard their Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring from their own Breaſts, and hire them out to be nurſed by Strangers; which thing <hi>for the moſt part</hi> being without any <hi>probable Cauſes,</hi> but only from an over-indulgent Fondneſs of their own Bodies, it comes to paſs, that to eaſe themſelves, they ſhuffle off the <hi>Honourable</hi> and <hi>Natural</hi> Pains of educating their own Children; and ſince this <hi>inhumane and degenerate Sloathfulneſs</hi> of Mothers is the cauſe of many Evils, we think
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58129:8"/>it the <hi>Duty of Preachers</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort Mothers not to deſert their Off-ſpring which they have borne, nor to deny thoſe the benefit of their Breaſts, whom they lately nouriſhed in their Womb, and ſuſtained with their own Bowels.</q> Now ſince our Reformation after it was brought to good Perfection in reſpect of Worſhip and Doctrine, was hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred by the Death of King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> from receiving the Conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation which was intended in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Church-Government and Eccleſiaſtical Laws; <hi>this Book,</hi> which gives us the moſt authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick account what was intended, cannot but be of great Authority with all that value the Judgment of our firſt Reformers. So that I may from this conclude, not only that it is every <hi>Preachers Duty</hi> to exhort Mothers to Nurſe their own, but alſo that it is the Duty of Mothers to comply with their Exhortations, and that if they do
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58129:9"/>otherwiſe, they betray an unjuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiable Contempt of theſe learned and pious Reformers of and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs for our Holy Religion.</p>
               <p>§ 8. To theſe Motives of my preſent undertaking I will add one more, viz. <hi>The hopes of routing this unnatural Cuſtom, and doing a deal of good thereby.</hi> I am ſure I have a very good Cauſe, and all the ſtrength of Reaſon and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion on my ſide, and the Impulſes of Nature to boot. I have alſo the more courteous and tractable Sex to deal with, who I may promiſe my ſelf, cannot all be obſtinate againſt the Evidences of their Duty, and the Inclinations of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Affection. And why ſhould I deſpair of reſcuing ſo great a part of Mankind from the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of an impudent Cuſtom, who ſeem ready to accept of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and to wait for ſome kind Deliverer to unlooſe their Fetters? Shall I doubt of a candid Recepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from that Sex, whom Nature
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58129:9"/>hath molded for Courteſie, and the Impreſſions of Religion and Compaſſion? Especially ſince, as <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> is ſaid to have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed in his Addreſſes to <hi>Admelus</hi> King of the <hi>Moloſſi,</hi> by bringing the King's Son in his Arms, I bring their own Children with me to ſecond my Perſuaſions by their prevailing Interceſſions, or indeed not ſo much to intercede for me, as to Petition for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p>§ 9. But if any rebellious Luſt, if Luxury, Pride or Avarice dare to appear againſt me, I have the Enſigns of Divine Authority to awe them, Evidences I mean from the Holy Scriptures and the Law of Nature to command their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. And though thoſe Books are ſaid to be moſt fatally De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive, which convince of Duty and yet fail of perſuading to it; yet what I have to propoſe, ſeems to me ſo likely, not only to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, but alſo to perſuade, that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58129:10"/>I hope it will do no harm but Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to the World. To conclude this Introduction, though theſe Reaſons prevailed to engage me to compoſe the enſuing Diſcourſe, yet for ſome Months I kept it by me, and could not perſuade my ſelf to publiſh it, till I met with his Grace the Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi>'s Sermons about the <hi>Education of Children</hi> lately pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd; wherein he recommends <hi>this as the firſt and moſt natural Duty incumbent on Parents toward their Children;</hi> and argues againſt the general <hi>neglect of it, as one of the great and crying Sins of this Age and Nation.</hi> And when I found my ſelf backed by <hi>ſuch</hi> Authority, I became uncapable of fearing any Senſures, or deſpairing of good Succeſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:58129:10"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Wherein the Caſe is briefly ſtated, and all thoſe Texts of Scripture alledged which relate to it: Toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Arguments and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences which reſult from them.</head>
               <p>§ 1. IT will not be neceſſary to ſpend much time in any elaborate ſtating of the Caſe, which I have undertaken. For it is agreed on all hands, that where there is a <hi>natural Inability</hi> or <hi>any bodily Infirmities</hi> in the Mother (<hi>real</hi> and not meerly <hi>pretended</hi>) that might have a <hi>pernicious Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> on her Nurſery, God who by his Providence hath cauſed thoſe Impediments, doth in ſuch caſes diſpenſe with this Duty.</p>
               <p>§ 2. So that this is the Caſe, <hi>Whether all Mothers, be their Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity what it will, who are neither diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enabled by any natural Defect, nor contracted Infirmity, are bound in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58129:11"/>Duty to give Suck themſelves to their own Children.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This I affirm, and ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to evince both <hi>from the Holy Scriptures</hi> recommending it as a Duty, the <hi>miſchievous Conſequences</hi> of neglecting it, and the <hi>Inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of all the uſual Plea's,</hi> which are made for ſuch neglect. Which three general Heads ſhall limit my enſuing Diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>§ 3. I begin with the <hi>Holy Scriptures.</hi> And becauſe I intend all poſſible plainneſs, without the Affectation of any artificial Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, I ſhall offer ſome Paſſages to Conſideration in the ſame or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as they lye in our Bibles, and make ſome obvious Remarks up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and ſuch Inferences as they will fairly bear, as I proceed.</p>
               <p>§ 4. And to begin with the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> the firſt paſſage we meet with to this purpoſe is in <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.7. where <hi>Sarah</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Gen. 21.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Who would have ſaid unto</hi> Abraham, <hi>that</hi> Sarah <hi>ſhould have given Children
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58129:11"/>Suck? For I have borne him a Son in his Old Age.</hi> We have <hi>Sarah</hi> a <hi>Nurſe</hi> as well as a <hi>Mother,</hi> though ſhe were the Wiſe not of a mean Peaſant, but of a mighty Prince; a Prince ſo Potent, that the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Kings courted his Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. A Prince abounding in Wealth and Power, the Maſter of a numerous Family, out of which he could number 318 Men fit to bear Arms, and all born in his Houſe. Now the Wiſe of ſuch an one could not want Conveniencies among ſo many Child-bearing Women that were in her Family, for the Nurſing of her Son by another; ſhe might have pleaded either <hi>State</hi> or <hi>Buſineſs</hi> to have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed her ſelf from the Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; eſpecially being grown in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to years, which made her leſs able to undergo the Fatigue of ſuch an Office; and having Beauty beyond what was ordinary at her Years, the decay of which, by the Toil and Watchings incident to a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58129:12"/>Nurſe, ſhe might have fairly pleaded. But waving all theſe Plea's, ſhe includes it her Duty to Nurſe the Fruit of her own Womb. For her words imply ſo much, <hi>Who would have ſaid to</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, <hi>that</hi> Sarah <hi>ſhould have given Suck? For I have borne him a Son,</hi> q. d. It is, I doubt nor, the Mothers Office, who <hi>bears</hi> the Child, to give it <hi>Suck;</hi> ſince then I have <hi>borne Abraham</hi> a Son, I muſt give it <hi>Suck</hi> and <hi>Nurſe</hi> it for him. Had it been uſual in thoſe times for vertuous Mothers to decline this Office, ſhe would not have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred her <hi>Nurſing</hi> a Son for <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> from her <hi>bearing</hi> of one; whereas the one implying the other intimates a neceſſary Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of the one from the other. And I do with the greater Confidence urge this Argument, becauſe it is St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi>'s Note on this Verſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>De Abrah.</hi> l. 1. c. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>The Moral uſe of this is, that Women are provoked to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber their Dignity, and to give Suck
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58129:12"/>to their Children. This is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Grace, the Honour of a Mother, whereby ſhe may recommend her ſelf to her own Husband.</hi> However this is certain, that this Pious Mother whom the Apoſtle propoſes as a Pattern to her Sex, and exhorts all Wives to <hi>imitate, that will do well,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.6.</note> and diſcharge Faithfully the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of their Relations, ſhe not only Nurſes her Son her ſelf, but plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intimates, that ſhe thought it her Duty to do ſo; though ſhe might have pleaded as many Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes as moſt of them can who decline this Office. They then that neglect the Duty, and have no better Pretences for ſuch their neglect, than thoſe which ſhe waved as inſufficient, are faulty at leaſt on this account, that they refuſe to imitate <hi>Sarah,</hi> whom the Apoſtle tells Wives they muſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, if <hi>they will do well.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§ 5. The next Text is in <hi>Gen.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen 49.25</note> 49.25. where the Patriarch <hi>Jacob</hi> having foretold the numerous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58129:13"/>of the Tribe of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> that like a <hi>Fruitful Vine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 49.22</note> 
                  <hi>whoſe Branches ſpread over the wall,</hi> it ſhould mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply into two Tribes; he aſſures him that the God who had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved and proſpered him, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his many Afflictions from his Brethren at firſt, and the <hi>Egyptians</hi> afterward,<note place="margin">V. 25.</note> ſhould <hi>Bleſs his Poſterity with Bleſſings of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven above, Bleſſings of the Deep, that lieth beneath, Bleſſings of the Breaſt and of the Womb,</hi> i.e. He would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for him an Inheritance, fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile and well watered with Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and Rivers, and a numerous Poſterity to enjoy it. Where it is to be obſerved, that the Bleſſings of the <hi>Breaſt</hi> and of the <hi>Womb</hi> are conjoyned, and a Promiſe made to this Tribe, that in order to its Increaſe, the Wives ſhould be Fruitful to bear, and Careful to Nurſe their own; that God would bleſs it with ſuch Women, as both would bear a numerous Off-ſpring and nouriſh their own Off-pring
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58129:13"/>with their own Breads. Whence the Inference is obvious, that as a <hi>Fruitful Wife</hi> is a <hi>Bleſſing,</hi> ſo when ſhe <hi>Nurſes</hi> her Children ſhe is a <hi>double Bleſſing</hi> to a Family. And as it is the Duty of every one to be as great a Bleſſing as ſhe can be to her Family, ſo ſuch Women muſt need be faulty, who after God hath given the <hi>Bleſſings of the Womb,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to compleat the Felicity by the <hi>Bleſſings of the Breaſt. The ten thouſands of</hi> Ephraim,<note place="margin">Deut. 33.17.</note> 
                  <hi>and the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of</hi> Manaſſeh, are the effects of theſe Bleſſings of the Breaſt and of the Womb; and intimates to us, that it is a likely way to obtain a numerous Poſterity, ſuch as <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi>'s was, for <hi>Fruitful Mothers</hi> to become themſelves <hi>Careful Nurſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§ 6. In <hi>Exod.</hi> 2.7, 8. when <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi>'s Daughter ſends to ſeek out for a Nurſe for <hi>Moſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 2.7, 8.</note> whom ſhe found expoſed, her Maid called <hi>the Childs Mother,</hi> and to her ſhe committed the little Nurſery. Now this may be conſidered,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:58129:14"/>either as the Act of the Royal Princeſs, the Contrivance of the Mother, or a Diſpenſation of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence. If we ſuppoſe that <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Daughter ſent on purpoſe to enquire out the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the expoſed Infant, we may conclude, ſhe thought her the fitteſt to Nurſe it. If it be rather thought, that the Mother laid her Daughter to watch and be ready if any ſuch occaſion ſhould hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, to call her rather than ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we have a commendable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of her Pious and Tender Concern for her Son, and carneſt deſire to Nurſe it her ſelf, rather than any other ſhould eaſe her of that Burden, and do that work for her. But if beſides either the Princeſs or the Mothers Intention God by his wiſe Providence deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined the Meſſenger to apply her ſelf to the Mother rather than any other Woman; we have the plain Determination of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that the Mother is fitteſt to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58129:14"/>Nurſe her own Child, and that it was beſt for this Infant, whom he intended for <hi>extraordinary Service,</hi> to have the advantage of the moſt <hi>ſuitable Nurſe.</hi> And it is further obſervable, that tho God would have <hi>Moſes</hi> trained up in Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the Egyptian Doctors, that he might be better qualified for the great Charge he was here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to undertake, yet he would not have him Suck Milk from an <hi>Egyptian Nurſe,</hi> which might have ſome bad Influence upon his Conſtitution and his Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</p>
               <p>§ 7. Numb. 11.12. <hi>Moſes</hi> thus expoſtulates with God, <hi>Have I conceived all this People? Have I begot them?</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> is as properly ſpoken of the Mother as of the Father. And Conception being peculiar to the Mother, it ſeems more reaſonable to render it in Analogy thereto. <hi>Have I brought them forth?</hi>
                  </note> or brought them forth) <hi>That thou ſhouldeſt ſay unto me, Carry them in thy Boſom, as a
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58129:15"/>Nurſing Father</hi> (or<note n="*" place="margin">There is no word in the Original for <hi>Father,</hi> only the Participle <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> is Maſculine; which yet the 72 render by <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> which for moſt part is Feminine, and ſignifies <hi>a Nurſe.</hi> And conſidering that Frequently in Hebrew one Gender is put for another, It may well be rendred a <hi>Nurſe</hi> here, as more ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to <hi>Conception</hi> and <hi>b<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring forth</hi> in the clauſe fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going.</note> as a Nurſe) <hi>beareth the Sucking Child to the Land, which thou ſwareſt unto their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi> Where <hi>Moſes</hi>s Argument ſtands upon this Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that whoſoever hath conceived and brought forth, ought to become Nurſe to the Sucking Child, and carry it in her Boſom. Unleſs this be granted; his Argument is invalid and nothing to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, the whole force of which ſeems to depend on that Suppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Judge then whether is more reaſonable to charge <hi>Moſes</hi> with an Abſurdity, or thoſe Women with an Immorality who neglect the Duty, which he takes for granted. He thought himſelf not obliged like a Nurſe to bear that froward People in his Boſom, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had not conceived them
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58129:15"/>nor brought them forth. Thereby evidently implying, that the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther who hath conceived and brought forth the Infant, ought (however froward it may be) to become its Nurſe, and Suckle it in her Boſom.</p>
               <p>§ 8. If we turn over to 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.22, 23. we find,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 1.22, 23.</note> that after <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah</hi> by her Prayers had obtained a Son, ſhe reſolves to lay aſide all other buſineſs, that ſhe might at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend this important one, the Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of her <hi>Samuel.</hi> She was a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of great Piety, who conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly went with her Hushand to the Sanctuary at the Feaſts. Yet know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how much God prefers Mercy before Sacrifice, ſhe reſolves to do ſo too; ſtaying at home to Nurſe her Son, as what ſhe apprehended more acceptable to God, than to appear at his Tabernacle with an Offering, and leave her Child at home to ſome Mercenary's Care. Whence we may conclude, that even the Pretences of Piety, which
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58129:16"/>of all others are the moſt plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, are not ſufficient to excuſe Mothers from this piece of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; and that if their Nurſery ſhould detain them for that time from a conſtant Attendance on God's publick Worſhip, he will in ſuch a caſe diſpence with their abſence, and accept their Charity toward their Infants inſtead of Devotion to himſelf. Perſons of Quality indeed may have ſuch aſſiſtance, that there can be no neceſſity of their confinement from Gods Houſe, eſpecially ſince none of them but are much nearer to a Church than <hi>Ramah</hi> was to <hi>Shiloh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bunting</hi>'s Travel of Patriarchs</note> which is computed to be twelve Miles, ſo that ordinarily they cannot have that Plea to make. Yet if any be in ſuch Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, that either the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick Worſhip of God or the Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing her Child muſt be neglected, ſhe hath here a preſident to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the caſe in favour of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity againſt the ſpecious Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:58129:16"/>of Devotion. And it is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther obſervable, that <hi>Hannah</hi>'s Nurſing of her firſt Son, was ſo far from hindring Fertility, that it rather procured a Divine Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, which multiplied her Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity <hi>to three Sons and two Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 2.21</note> ſufficient to reſcue her from her Rivals Taunts, and rank her in the Catalogue of fruitful Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. So vain is that popular Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, that Nurſing is an Impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to Fruitfulneſs, and to be declin'd by great Perſons for the better ſecuring of Succeſſion by a numerous Poſterity; for if thoſe bear faſter who dry up their Breaſts, they that Nurſe their Children commonly bear longer, and bring more up to an Health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Maturity; which comes to paſs, partly through their greater Care, and partly through Gods Bleſſing on their exemplary Piety.</p>
               <p>§ 9. There is a Story in 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 3.21. of two Women of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous Character,<note place="margin">1. Kings 3.21.</note> being ſtiled
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58129:17"/>
                  <hi>Harlots;</hi> nor will I take the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage ſome Interpreters give me, to ſoften that Denomination into Victuallers; but will ſuppoſe them to have been bad Women, yet obſerving ſomething remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably good in one of them, it is the more to be took notice of. Now it is evident that the one of theſe Harlots was a tender Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, though ſhe had been an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſt Woman, and loved her Child very well, however ſhe came by it; and it is recorded of her, that ſhe her ſelf gave it Suck. Which is an Argument, that though ſhe had not Vertue ſufficient to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure her Chaſtity, yet ſhe was not ſo overgrown with Vice, as to have obliterated Natural Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The better of theſe two Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots hath the Character of a <hi>Fond Mother,</hi> and her pleading before King <hi>Solomon,</hi> that ſhe <hi>roſe to give her Child Suck,</hi> is an Intimation that this was a Duty of good E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem in thoſe days, and that it
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58129:17"/>would make ſomething for her that ſhe had done ſo. And how can thoſe Mothers pretend Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to their Children, who at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain not to the Tenderneſs of this <hi>good-natur'd Harlot?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>ſect; 10. In the Book of <hi>Job,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 39.16</note> c. 39.16. there is an elegant Deſcription of the <hi>Oſtriches</hi> ſtupid neglect of her young ones, wherein this is eſpecially took notice of, That <hi>ſhe hardened her ſelf againſt her young ones, as though they were not hers.</hi> Whereby the Spirit of God inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates it to be an Aggravation of Hard-heartedneſs to deal hardly with thoſe that are <hi>young,</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally where natural Relation ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liges to a tender Regard: And that the nearer any come to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble the <hi>Oſtriches</hi> Obduracy, in neglecting to take care of their Off ſpring, the more unnatural and cruel they may be juſtly deemed. And if it be a piece of Hardſhip to turn off a tender In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant to a Mercenary Nurſe (as I
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58129:18"/>doubt not but in the ſequel of this Diſcourſe will be manifeſt) thoſe Mothers muſt be accounted more <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nnatural</hi> than the <hi>Oſtrich,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have not ſo much Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidity.</p>
               <p>§ 11. In <hi>Pſal.</hi> 29.9. the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt ſays,<note place="margin">Pſal. 22.9</note> 
                  <hi>Thou didſt make me hope, when I was upon my Mothers Breaſts.</hi> Now hope is an act of Reaſon, not to be exerted by an Infant not yet arrived to the Exerciſe of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, yet here in a Poetical ſtile at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to ſuch an one; to inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, that the Care God takes of Infants, and the early Proviſion he hath made for them, by filling their Mothers <hi>Breaſts</hi> as ſoon as they have left her <hi>Womb,</hi> is an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument that Mankind is under the Care of God's Providence, and of ſufficient force to engage <hi>even Infants</hi> to hope in God, if they were capable. And hence it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that it is the Intention of the God of Nature, in furniſhing the Mother with full Breaſts, to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:58129:18"/>oblige her to miniſter thereby to his Providence for the Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her Child. Moreover the Pſalmiſt's uſing ſuch a Phraſe as this, doth not only imply that he was nurſed by his own Mother, but alſo that it was uſual in thoſe days, for Mothers themſelves to perform that Office. The Practiſe of our Age would ſcarce allow us to expreſs the time of <hi>Infancy</hi> by <hi>hanging on the Mothers Breaſts,</hi> wherein ſo few enjoy that Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. And if we grant that ſuch Idioms of Language are founded on the prevailing Cuſtoms of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, we may conclude from this Phraſe (and that of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s, who expreſſes a <hi>Brother</hi> Periphraſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, by one that <hi>ſucked the Breaſts of his Mother</hi>) that it was in thoſe days very common,<note place="margin">Cant. 8.1.</note> and accounted moſt reaſonable, that the Mother ſhould Nurſe at her Breaſts all the Children ſhe had born in her Womb.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:58129:19"/>
               <p>§ 12. The Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> exaggerates the Extremity of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> by this Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance, that it had made Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Cruel to their Infants, and uncapable of giving them Suck, <hi>Lam.</hi> 4.23. Even the <hi>Sea-monſters draw out the Breaſts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lam. 4.23.</note> 
                  <hi>they give Suck to their young ones; but the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of my People is become Cruel, like the Oſtriches in the Wilderneſs.</hi> It's true, it ſeems to be not ſo much from the <hi>Hardneſs</hi> of their <hi>Hearts,</hi> as of the <hi>Times,</hi> that the Daughters of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> do not that for their Off-ſpring, which the very <hi>Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſters</hi> do for theirs, and which no Creature on the Land is ſo much <hi>a Brute</hi> as to neglect, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the <hi>Oſtrich,</hi> whoſe ſtupidity is ſuch, that ſhe leaves her Eggs in the Sand and takes no further care of them, no nor of her young ones neither, after the heat of the Sun and of the Sand hath hatched them. And nothing certainly, but the Extremity of Famine, could
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58129:19"/>make the Daughters of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſo Cruel, that <hi>no Monſter at Sea, no Brute on Land,</hi> can parallel them, except the <hi>Oſtrich.</hi> How then can they excuſe themſelves, who neglect their Children as much <hi>out of Luxury,</hi> and in the <hi>midst of Plenty,</hi> as thoſe <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did <hi>through Famine?</hi> The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet thought this an Inſtance fit to exaggerate the great Miſery of a Famine, that it conſtrained Mothers to that which Nature moſt abhors. We may then rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably conclude, That he would have paſſed a very ſevere Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure on thoſe Mothers that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Cruel in the midſt of Plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and for that very reaſon too, becauſe they abound with Plenty. They are more unnatural than Sea-Monſters, that draw out their Breaſts to their young ones, whilſt theſe turn theirs off to ſome mean and Mercenary Neighbour.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:58129:20"/>
               <p>§ 13. I ſhall conclude my Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations out of the <hi>Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſ. 9.14.</note> with that paſſage of the Prophet <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 9.14. <hi>Give them, O Lord, What wilt thou give them? Give them a miſcarrying Womb and dry Breaſts.</hi> For whether he pray for this as a <hi>Bleſſing</hi> for <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that they may not be more <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable</hi> (in the common Slaughter of their Country) for <hi>their Ferti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> as our Lord Chriſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounces ſuch comparatively Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in the Deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> that were <hi>barren and had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver born,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 23.29.</note> 
                  <hi>and whoſe Paps had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver given, Suck.</hi> Or whether he denounce it as a Curſe, that their Women ſhould be Barren and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with a <hi>miſcarrying Womb and dry Breaſts;</hi> which way ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver we underſtand it, it affords us this Concluſion, that the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God in the Scriptures makes <hi>dry Breaſts</hi> as well as a <hi>miſcarrying Womb,</hi> the Periphraſis of <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renneſs;</hi> thereby declaring it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:58129:20"/>unnatural for a Mother by artificial Applications to <hi>dry her Breaſts,</hi> as to <hi>force Abortion;</hi> and that where God gives a fruitful Womb, he expects ordinarily that the Breaſts ſhould give Suck. God gives dry Breaſts aſ a Curſe to ſome, as an Affliction to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; but they that invite that, whether Curſe or Affliction, to themſelves by voluntary Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, <hi>love not Bleſſing,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>it ſhall be far from them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus have I lead you through the Old Teſtament, and ſhewed you the laudable. Examples it gives Mothers for Nurſing their Children, and the plain Intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (at leaſt) of the Divine Pleaſure, that they ſhould do like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
               <p>§ 14. I proceed to ſet before you ſuch paſſages of the <hi>New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament</hi> as are of the ſame Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and furniſh us with ſome Proofs of the caſe propoſed.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:58129:21"/>
               <p>In the <hi>Goſpel</hi> we read of a Woman, who in a Rapture of Admiration at Chriſt's Diſcourſes, cries out,<note place="margin">Luke 11.27.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed is the Womb that bare thee, and the Paps which thou haſt Sucked.</hi> Which ſhews that ſhe took it for granted, that the Mother of our Lord gave him Suck. And upon this evidence, and becauſe we find that <hi>Joſeph</hi> in his Flight with his Holy In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant into <hi>Egypt,</hi> took none other with him but the Bleſſed Virgin, it hath been unanimouſly agreed, that ſhe was the Nurſe as well as the Mother of Chriſt. And ſince this Virgin, not only for the Nobility of her Extraction (tho now ſunk into a meaner For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune) but eſpecially for the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of her Manners, hath juſtly been reputed the Glory of her Sex, none can have an Example more worthy of her Imitation. <hi>God choſe not</hi> (ſaith one of the Ancients) <hi>any ordinary Woman to be the Mother of Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apud Juſt. Mart quaeſt. &amp; reſp. ad Orthod. <hi>q. 136. p. 375</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>but one that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:58129:21"/>excelled all other Women in Vertue; whom he therefore pronounces Bleſſed for her Vertues, for which he vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed her to be his Mother.</hi> And ſuch eminent Vertues in this Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Virgin recommend her as a fit Example for the beſt and the greateſt of her Sex to imitate.</p>
               <p>§ 15. In the next place it may be obſerved, That the Chriſtian Religion hath adopted into Law and Duty, all thoſe things which generally approve themſelves to the unprejudiced Reaſon of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind,<note place="margin">Phil. 4.8.</note> to be <hi>things Honeſt, Lovely, and of good Report. Things honest</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>Grave,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.11.</note> or becoming Chaſt and Vertuous Matrons. <hi>Things Lovely</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) which are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally <hi>Grateful</hi> to all wiſe and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Perſons, and <hi>apt to procure Love. Things of good Report,</hi> which are apt to procure to the Perſons that do them, and to the Religion which they profeſs, good Eſteem and Commendation. Now I dare appeal to all the World,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:58129:22"/>whether thoſe few Perſons of Quality and Honour are not ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally looked upon with a Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration and Eſteem, who having broke through an unreaſonable Cuſtom, and preferred the good of their Children before a Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtick Privilege of Greatneſs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Nurſes to their own Off-ſpring. Who doth not approve of this as an Action becoming the <hi>Gravity</hi> of a Chaſt Lady? In whoſe Eyes is it not a Spectacle moſt <hi>Lovely?</hi> What vertuous and ſober Perſons but think it very Praiſe-worthy? From this general Precept of Chriſtianity therefore we muſt conclude this generally to be the Duty of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Matrons.</p>
               <p>§ 16. That of the Apoſtles 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.7. is not here to be omitted.<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 2.7.</note> 
                  <hi>We were gentle among you, even as a Nurſe cheriſheth her Children.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Where two things are obſervable: Firſt, That the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> is here ſtiled a <hi>Nurſe;</hi> for it
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:58129:22"/>is <hi>her own Children,</hi> not anothers, whom the Nurſe is ſaid to Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh. Whence it ſeems, that the Apoſtle taking it for granted, that the Mother is her ſelf the Nurſe, implies it the Duty of all Mothers to undertake that Office. Secondly, That St. <hi>Paul</hi> chooſes to expreſs his own mild and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Behaviour toward the Church, by a Mother <hi>Nurſing her own.</hi> Which implies, that the Mothers Care is the greateſt, and her Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage the moſt Tender toward her Nurſery, who is influenced by Natural Affection, and not meerly by hopes of Reward. It would have been a Diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Apoſtles mild and tender Behaviour towards them, to have compared him with a Mercenary Nurſe, that looks to anothers Child for hire, and is rarely ſo careful of it as its own Mother, to whom Nature di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates the moſt compaſſionate Concern for its welfare.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:58129:23"/>
               <p>§ 17. Hitherto in the next place belongs the Character which the Apoſtle gives of a <hi>Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow indeed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.10.</note> who is to be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the Churches Charity. He requires, among other Virtues, that <hi>ſhe be well reported for good Works, and that ſhe have brought up Children.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> The Greek word denotes <hi>Nurſing Children.</hi> Our Lexicons cite <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> for the uſe of it, and it is obſerable, that he uſes the Verb, from which this is compounded to denote this pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Office of the Mother in his Oeconomicks, which becauſe it gives us the Judgment of that great Philoſopher,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ariſt. Oeco.</hi> l. 1. c. 3. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. And <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Acts 13.18. is in the Margent of our Bibles rendred, <hi>Suffered them, as a Nurſe beareth the Child.</hi> And by Dr. <hi>Hammond, Carried them as a Nurſe;</hi> who concludes the right reading to be <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> from <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, to do the Office of a Nurſe; who not only bears the Child in her Arms, but feeds and ſuſtains it too, as God did the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the Wilderneſs. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> is alſo rendred a Nurſe in the Text aforecited, 1 Theſſ. 2.7.</note> I will here tranſcribe. <hi>As to their Children,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>both Parents equally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:58129:23"/>to their Generation; but their Offices are peculiar as to their future Improvement. The Mothers Office is to Nurſe, and the Fathers to Educate or Correct.</hi> In the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> thoſe Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows who had nurſed their own Children, were reputed to have done a <hi>good Work;</hi> and they that had not done ſo, were judged for that very reaſon unworthy of the Churches Charity. And as we may very well preſume, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle would not have exempted any indigent Widow from that Privilege for no Fault; but that it was a thing Scandalous and of very ill report, for any Chriſtian Matron not to have nurſed her own Children.</p>
               <p>§ 18. I ſhall only add, That among the Duties of the younger Women, ſuch as are not yet paſt Child bearing, they are to be taught, <hi>That they love their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> Tit. 2.4. For if it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, that Nurſing their own
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:58129:24"/>Children is a very proper and natural Teſtimony to <hi>maternal Love,</hi> and the moſt likely means not only to expreſs but increaſe their natural Affection toward them; I ſee not how they can evade the Obligation of this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept. For the Law of Love obliges a Mother to all proper Means and Ways of teſtifying and maintaining her Love, and conſequently to this. The greateſt Ladies are bound to love their Children as well as the meaneſt Beggar, and conſequently to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect no proper means of ſhewing and cheriſhing it: So that unleſs they deny Nurſing of them to be ſuch, they muſt hence conclude it to be their Duty.</p>
               <p>§ 19. But before I put an end to this Chapter, it is requiſite that I take notice of ſome paſſages which ſeem to diſcountenance the Cauſe I have been pleading for; leaſt my pretermitting of them ſhould make any to fancy
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:58129:24"/>it was not for the Weakneſs but Cogency and Weight of the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection that is raiſed from them. I mean thoſe Texts which men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſome Nurſes who were <hi>not the Mothers</hi> of the Children whom <hi>they Nurſed.</hi> Such was <hi>Deborah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 35.8. Ruth 4.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Rebecca</hi>'s Nurſe; <hi>Naomi,</hi> who <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Nurſe</hi> to her Grandſon by <hi>Ruth; Mephiboſheth</hi>'s Nurſe,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 4.4. 2 Kings 11.2.</note> who let him fall as ſhe ſled; and <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſh</hi>'s Nurſe that was hid with him.</p>
               <p>§ 20. Now in anſwer to theſe Inſtances, I ſhall only offer theſe things. 1. That in ſome caſes it is ſo far from being a neceſſary Duty, that it is not poſſible for the Child to be nurſed by its own Mother: As if ſhe die in Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, or lye under ſome natural Inability from the want of Nip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples or Suck. And in ſuch caſes recourſe muſt be had to ſome other means for the Infants Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation. And for what appears to the contrary, this may be the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:58129:25"/>occaſion of the Subſtitution of ſome of the Nurſes abovenamed. <hi>Joaſh</hi>'s Nurſe it's probable ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied the Office of his deceaſed Mother; for his Aunts Care about his Preſervation makes it likely, that his Mother was ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dead before, or was Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in the univerſal Butchery of the Royal Family by <hi>Athaliah.</hi> 2. Some of thoſe before named were <hi>dry Nurſes, Aſſiſtants</hi> only not <hi>Subſtitutes</hi> to the Mother: Such doubtleſs was <hi>Naomi,</hi> whoſe Age and long Widowhood makes it very unlikely, that ſhe ſhould be able to give her Grandchild Suck. And <hi>Pareus</hi> from <hi>Jacob</hi>'s ſolemn Mourning at the Death of <hi>Deborah,</hi> concludes her to have been called <hi>Rebecca</hi>'s Nurſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe had aſſiſted her in the Nurſing of her Children, and not as if ſhe had given her Suck; and that for this reaſon <hi>Jacob</hi> after his Mothers Death, had taken her into his own Family. 3. If it be
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:58129:25"/>granted moſt probable (as to me it ſeems to be) that <hi>Mephibo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth</hi>'s Nurſe gave him Suck, and was ſubſtituted in the room of his Mother; this will be no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage to our Cauſe. For as it was his great Unhappineſs to loſe his Mother betimes, ſo it was a greater, to be committed to ſuch a Nurſe, as by her Careleſneſs (perhaps) made him a Cripple to his Death. Laſtly, I cannot upon the whole, remember one Inſtance out of the Holy Scriptures, of any either good or bad Mother, who did her ſelf deliver her Child to another to Nurſe, nor is it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that any of the Nurſes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanced above, were made ſuch by the Mothers of the Children themſelves whilſt they were liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and therefore they reach not to Patronize their Caſe, who or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily do ſo.</p>
               <p>§ 21. Thus I have given a juſt and impartial account of the Teſtimonies of the <hi>Holy Scripture</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:58129:26"/>both of the <hi>Old and New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which reſpect our preſent ſubject; and if they have been impartially conſidered, they muſt needs have ſatisfied you, that thoſe Mothers are moſt conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Dictates of God's Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in his Word, who <hi>themſelves Nurſe their own Children.</hi> And all the Favour I deſire of any Mother upon the Survey of the forementioned particulars, is to allow her own Conſcience to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, whether God hath not in his Word plainly enough de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared this to be her Duty. And then, I hope, none will be ſo <hi>Vain</hi> or <hi>Impious,</hi> as to oppoſe <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom</hi> or the <hi>Privilege of her Rank,</hi> to ſuch <hi>indiſputable Authority</hi> and <hi>plain Convictions</hi> of her <hi>Duty.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:58129:26"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Wherein are manifeſted the great Miſchiefs which Mothers by tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring the Nurſing of their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to other Women, threaten their Families with; both in point of <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> and that <hi>Mutual Affection</hi> which ought to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the ſeveral Branches of it.</head>
               <p>§ 1. MY propoſed Method leads me how to the ſecond part of my undertaking, viz. To <hi>conſider and repreſent the Miſchievous Conſequences which fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently reſult from Mothers expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their Children to be nurſed by other Women,</hi> and cannot other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be ſo ſurely prevented, as by diſcharging this Office themſelves. And they either reſpect the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily</hi> or the <hi>Child.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>The whole Family may ſuffer great prejudice by this unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Cuſtom:</hi> And that both in
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:58129:27"/>point of Succeſſion, and that mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Affection which ought to be among the ſeveral Branches of it, and is neceſſary to its flouriſhing Proſperity.</p>
               <p>§ 2. 1. <hi>The Families of the Great and the Rich eſpecially are in danger to be injured hereby in the Succeſſion.</hi> None are ſo much concerned, as Perſons of Honour and Eſtates, to preſerve the Succeſſion of both to their own Off-ſpring, nor are any in ſo much danger as they to be injured that way. The poor Man needs not fear a Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſititious Brood; for who will be deſirous to obtrude a Child on him to inherit Beggary? But if a poor Tenant have a fair Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to thruſt her own or Friends Child into the room of her Landlords Heir, or can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive to make him paſs for the Son of a Wealthy Tradeſman, it requires a deal of Honeſty to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Temptation. Now if it be conſidered how mutable the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:58129:27"/>Countenance of an Infant is; what Alterations a few days make in the Lineaments of its Face, it may be judged no hard thing to deceive the moſt Criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Mother after a Months ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. So that either if the Nurſe have a mind to make her own Child, or be hired to make ſome others a Fortune; or if ſhe have Overlaid her Nurſery, and to conceal the Crime, cloath ſome other about the ſame Age in its Spoils, perhaps the moſt curious Inſpection may not be able to diſcern the Cheat. I am ſure the booriſh and degenerate Rudeneſs of ſome, who paſs for the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of very Polite, Ingenious and good humoured Parents, give too much cauſe to ſuſpect them Changlings. Nor is this a bare Suppoſition without any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, for <hi>Valerius Maximus</hi> tells us,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Val. Max.</hi> l. 9. c. 15.3.</note> That in the Reign of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> one pretended to be the Son of his Siſter <hi>Octavia,</hi> affirming,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:58129:28"/>That by reaſon of his great Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs he had been changed for the Nurſes own Son. It's true the Cheat ſucceeded not, yet <hi>Octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via</hi>'s putting of her Son off to be Nurſed by a Stranger, gave an opportunity to attempt it: And perhaps the reaſon that ſo few Nurſes art detected in ſuch like Attempts, is becauſe they fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſucceed better, being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected only where they fail. Yet one remarkable Inſtance more there is, How <hi>Arthebar,</hi> or (as others call him) <hi>Artabanus</hi> King of <hi>Epirus</hi> was more ſucceſsfully impoſed on, having his Child changed at Nurſe, and the Son of a mean Knight introduced into his Family. Which Treaſon the Nurſe at length, though too late diſcovering, occaſioned a Bloody War, wherein both Pretenders were ſlain, and the Kingdom it ſelf Uſurped by <hi>Alexander</hi> the Brother of that <hi>Olympias,</hi> who was <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great's Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:58129:28"/>And to prevent ſuch Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſititious Baſtardies, <hi>Lycurgus</hi> the Famous <hi>Spartan</hi> Law-giver enacted, That the nobleſt <hi>Spartan</hi> Women<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> even their Kings Wives, ſhould at the leaſt Nurſe their eldeſt Son. And <hi>Plutarch</hi> reports, That the ſecond Son of <hi>Themiſtes</hi> the ſeventh King of the <hi>Lacede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monians,</hi> ſucceeded his Father, only becauſe he had been nurſed by his own. Mother, whereas the eldeſt had ſucked the Breaſts of a Stranger. Now as the Mothers Nurſing her ſelf is a ſure way to prevent any ſuch Cheat of the Nurſe; ſo it is a Security to the Husband, that ſhe hath not her ſelf, to eſcape the Infamy of Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renneſs., Conſented to the intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing of anothers Child into his Family. And it is the Note of St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> upon <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.7. <q>That therefore <hi>Sarah</hi> give Suck, to make it more credible, that ſhe was truly a Mother, leaſt any by reaſon of her Age ſhould
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:58129:29"/>have ſuſpected the Child to have been Suppoſititious. For the Milk in her Breaſts might ſatisfie the moſt Diſtruſtful, that <hi>Iſaac</hi> was her genuine Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring, and that beyond all Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation ſhe was become a Mother.</q> Hence I conclude, that the Quality of any Woman is ſo far from being a reaſonable Excuſe from undertaking this part in the Education of her Child, that it rather increaſes her Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation. For the greateſt Care ought to be taken in preventing the Obtruſion of a Spurious Iſſue on the Families and Succeſſions, where there is the moſt Danger.</p>
               <p>§ 3. 2. I come to ſhew Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, That as it is neceſſary to the Happineſs of every Family, that there be mutual Indearments be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the ſeveral Branches of it: So the putting of Children out to be nurſed by others, is a very likely way to hinder them, and the contrary to promote them;
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:58129:29"/>which I ſhall manifeſt in theſe three Particulars, <hi>viz.</hi> In reſpect of the <hi>Mothers Affection towards the Child,</hi> The <hi>Childs towards its Mother,</hi> and <hi>The Children of the ſame Parents towards one another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§ 4. Firſt, It is very unlikely that thoſe <hi>Mothers, who transfer the Nurſing of their Children to others, ſhould ordinarily love them as tenderly as thoſe that make them their own Care.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>A Gell.</hi> l. 12. c. 1. <hi>ad fin.</hi>
                  </note> When the Infant is exil'd from its Mothers ſight, that warmth of Love, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives new Vigor from the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent view of its Object, cools by degrees and languiſhes; whilſt the Interpoſition of other Objects ſoon weans her from that poor Exile, who becomes abroad al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as much forgotten, as if it had been laid in the Grave. It is not rare to obſerve, That Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-Children are more dear to their Nurſes than their Mothers; and Mothers for the moſt part are fondeſt of thoſe whom they
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:58129:30"/>have nurſed themſelves. And it is too common an Obſervation, That ſome Ladies ſhew a greater Fondneſs toward their Dogs than their Children,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ladies Calling,</hi> Part 2. Sect. 2. § 26.</note> 
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">Shewing thoſe to all Comers, when in many days Converſe one ſhall hear nothing, whence it may be known that they have any Children.</hi> Concerning which we have a remarkable Story in <hi>Plutarch,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plut. In Pencl<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> How that <hi>Ceſar</hi> once ſeeing ſome Strangers at <hi>Rome,</hi> who were People of Quality, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying up and down with them in their Arms and Boſoms young Puppy-dogs and Munkies, and hugging and making much of them, took occaſion to ask, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Women in their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try were not uſed to bear Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. By that Princely Reprimand gravely reflecting upon ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as ſpend and laviſh that Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and Kindneſs (which Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath impleated in us) on Brute Creatures, though it be due
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:58129:30"/>and owing only to humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, thoſe of our own Kind. Now there can no account ſo likely be given of any Womans greater Fondneſs, of Brutes, than of their own Children, but that theſe being nurſed abroad, their Dogs are more converſant with them than they. I muſt confeſs (what a. Learned Man objects) that many Ladies,<note place="margin">Towerſon <hi>on the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandm.</hi> p. 237.</note> who place their Children abroad, are very tender of them, and ſometimes more Fond than Women of meaner Birth and Fortunes, who for the moſt part Nurſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: Nor would I therefore be underſtood to intend the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Cenſure for all Mothers that decline this Office. In ſome, nay in many, I hope, Duty and natural Affection triumph over this Temptation. However it is a Temptation that prevails on too many, and they that are Wiſe, will for that reaſon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude it beſt and ſafeſt to avoid it.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:58129:31"/>St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> made this Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Amb. de Abr.</hi> l. 1. c. 7.</note> That Mothers generally love thoſe beſt whom they have Suckled at their own Breaſts.<note place="margin">Plut. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, p. 3. Id. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, p. 496.</note> And <hi>Plutarch</hi> concludes this the principal Intention of Nature, in giving the Mother a Capacity of being a Nurſe, and in placing her Breaſts ſo conveniently for the embracing of her little Nurſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that ſhe may receive freſh Endearments every Moment from thoſe intimate Embraces.<note n="*" place="margin">Nay, God himſelf ſuppoſes this apt to create a great Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs in the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when he ſays, <hi>Iſa</hi> 49.15. <hi>Can a Woman forget her Sucking Child, that ſhe ſhould not have Compaſſion on the Son of her Womb?</hi> When the Woman makes the <hi>Son of her Womb her Suck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Child,</hi> or her own Nurſery, it is a thing next to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, that ſhe ſhould fail in the Affection and Care of a Mother toward it.</note> And if this be granted as a moſt likely means to increaſe the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Love to her Child, ſhe that exiles her little ones, takes the way hugely to cool, if not quite extinguiſh it.</p>
               <p>§ 5. Secondly, <hi>This is the way to alienate the Childs Affections
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:58129:31"/>from its Mother.</hi> Some Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians derive the Latin word <hi>Lac</hi> (Milk) from <hi>lacio</hi> (to allure) as concluding no way ſo likely to allure the Child to love its Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as Nurſing it with her Milk. She performs indeed but half the Office, and conſequently earns but <hi>half of that Love</hi> which otherwiſe is due to a Mother who only bears her Child and then turns it off. And I never yet met with any one Inſtance to contradict the Obſervation of a Learned Prelate to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, viz. <hi>That many cruel Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants have killed their Mothers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Taylor</hi>'s Grand Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. p. 21. § 10.</note> 
                  <hi>yet none ever offered Violence to his Nurſe.</hi> And this ſhews that bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Womb is not ſo invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olable an Obligation to Love, as Nurſing at the Breaſt. We read of one of the <hi>Gracchi</hi> returning to <hi>Rome</hi> from his Victories in <hi>Aſia,</hi> that he preſented his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a Jewel of Silver, and his Nurſe with a Girdle of Gold;
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:58129:32"/>giving this reaſon for the prefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the latter,<note place="margin">Roderic. de Caſtro de Mulier. morbis.</note> That when his Mother, after his Birth, caſt him off, his Nurſe took him for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken as he was to her Breaſts, and cheriſhed him in her kind Embraces. This is manifeſt, that Love deſconds more ſtrongly than it aſcends, ſo that it is not likely that the Childs Affections to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards its Parents ſhould exceed theirs towards it. And therefore ſuch a Mother hath reaſon to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the leaſt Love from her Children, who hath ſhewed the leaſt toward them Perhaps whilſt ſhe is in Proſperity, and ſtands in no need of their Love, Intereſt may oblige them to carry civilly toward her: Yet it is to be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected that they have no ſuch grounds in Nature, as will main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a conſtant Fervour of Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction againſt the Frowardneſs or Misfortunes of an Unnatural Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. I do not affirm this to be a conſtant Effect of that Cauſe,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:58129:32"/>for ſometimes perhaps the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers After-care may make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends for the firſt Unkindneſs: Sometimes extraordinary good Nature in the Child may conquer the Reſentments of this early Neglect, or the Influences of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Grace may triumph over this Temptation. It is enough for my purpoſe that it is a Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a Temptation which oft prevails on a Graceleſs Child, to requite hits Mothers Rejection of him with the like Unkindneſs: And this is reaſon enough to oblige all Mothers to prevent it by their early Care and Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in Nurſing.</p>
               <p>§ 6. Thirdly, As the Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Families very much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon the mutual Love of the ſeveral Branches of it among themſelves; ſo the Mothers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing them that <hi>common Nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> which were likely to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote it, is too juſtly chargeable with the Miſchiefs which reſult
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:58129:33"/>from their mutual Unkindneſſes. We read of <hi>Scipio Aſiaticus,</hi> that though he rejected the Importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of his Brother <hi>Africanus,</hi> in behalf of ten Soldiers who were condemned for offering Violence to the <hi>Veſtals;</hi> yet he pardoned them at the requeſt of his Foſter-Siſter: And being asked the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why he did more for his Nurſes Daughter than for his own Mothers Son, he returned this anſwer, <hi>I eſteem her rather to be my Mother who brought me up, than her that brought me forth and then forſook me.</hi> Which ſhews both that his Nurſe had more of his Love than his Mother, and alſo her who ſucked the ſame Milk, than he who had lain in the ſame Womb.<note place="margin">Plut. In Catone.</note> I remember <hi>Plutarch</hi> reports of <hi>Cato,</hi> that wiſe <hi>Roman,</hi> that as he obliged his Wife to give her Children Suck with her own Breaſts, ſo alſo to let the Children of his Slaves Suck her too, that by partaking of the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:58129:33"/>ſame Nouriſhment, a Natural Affection might be inſtilled into them toward his Son. And the frequent Inſtances of many great Perſons Kindneſs and Liberality toward their Foſter-Brothers, is an Argument how prevalent this Method is, of propagating the Streams of Love from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Fountain of the Breaſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all the partakers of it. And the too common Obſervation of Fraternal Diſcords, as it is matter of Melancholly Conſideration, ſo it ought to oblige Mothers to neglect no means any way likely to prevent them; eſpecially to joyn them all at her Breaſts, that they may be more united in their Lives.</p>
               <p>§ 7. Thus have I demonſtrated how much the good of <hi>Families</hi> obliges all Mothers, eſpecially Perſons of Quality, to Nurſe their own Children, that they may more ſurely prevent all Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities of <hi>wronging their own Heir,</hi>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:58129:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>of <hi>alienating themſelves from their Children, or their Children from them,</hi> or <hi>from one another.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> In which is contained an account of the Inconveniencies reſulting to <hi>the Children</hi> themſelves that are Nurſed by Strangers, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of <hi>their Bodies,</hi> either through the Nurſes want of Care, the unſuitable Nouriſhment, or Contagious Diſeaſes that may be tranſmitted in her Milk.</head>
               <p>§ 1. I Come now Secondly to repreſent the Miſchiefs that threaten the <hi>Children them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elves,</hi> which are deſerted by their own Mothers to be Nurſed by Strangers.</p>
               <p>It is a pretty Obſervation which St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> makes on <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.25. where <hi>Cham</hi>'s Curſe is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in his Sons name, <hi>Curſed
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:58129:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>be</hi> Canaan, <hi>viz.</hi> That it is a greater Puniſhment to wicked <hi>Cham</hi> to be Curſed in his Race, than in his own Perſon. The Wounds which tender Parents receive in the Miſeries of their Children, are much more ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble than their own perſonal Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities. This Conſideration then in all reaſon ſhould touch all Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the moſt ſenſible part, and be of the greateſt force with them, <hi>viz.</hi> That others Nurſing of them is likely to be extreamly prejudicial to their Children, both in reſpett <hi>of their Bodies and their Minds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§ 2. I ſhall in this Chapter ſhew how <hi>the Health of the Childs Body</hi> is endangered by putting it to a Stranger to be nurſed, and that theſe ſeveral ways, Either by <hi>her want of Care intending it,</hi> by <hi>yielding it unſuitable Nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> or by <hi>tranſmitting Diſeaſes</hi> to it.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:58129:35"/>
               <p>§ 3. <hi>A Mercenary Nurſe is not likely to take ſo much Care of the Child as its own Mother.</hi> In our Bibles we read of <hi>Mephiboſheſth</hi>'s Miſhap received from his Nurſe, who letting him fall out of her Arms as ſhe fled, made him ever after unable to go. And who ſees not how many carry about them to their death, the Marks of their Nurſes Careleſneſs? And no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, for Natural Affection will make the Mother more watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful over and patient with the Frowardneſs of her own Babe, than ſhe can expect an Hireling to be.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>De Educ.</hi> lib. P. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>The Mother is fitteſt to Nurſe,</hi> ſaith <hi>Plutarch, becauſe ſhe will treat the Child with more Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion and Care, as being influenced by an inward Tenderneſs, which bears date from its firſt being: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Love of a Nurſe is only Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dititiouſ, the reſult not of Nature but of Wages.</hi> It is reaſonable to expect the Miſtreſs of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily more careful of her own
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:58129:35"/>Domeſtick Affairs, than any of her Mercenary Servants, ſince the firſt is obliged by a greater In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt than the latter; ſo that where the Miſtreſs is Negligent, we do not ordinarily expect the Maid ſhould be more Induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. And where the Mothers Love can ſuffer a Child to be expoſed, whom Nature hath intereſted in its Welfare, none can wonder if a Stranger neglect it. For indeed how can it be expected, that an Hireling ſhould endure all the Tediouſneſſes and Inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies attending the Nurſing of a little, helpleſs, perhaps Froward Infant; when the Mother, to whom Natural Affection ſhould have endeared the Employment, out of Softneſs and Luxury de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines it as a Burden? Or why hath God generally inſpired the Mother with a greater Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs toward the Child, but for this very end, That thereby ſhe may be enabled to digeſt more
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:58129:36"/>eaſily the <hi>little <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nhandſomneſſes</hi> (as one phraſes it) which others Will nauſeate,<note place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Taylour</hi>'s Grand Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.</note> and ſubmit to thoſe Fatigues that none elſe will for its Preſervation, whilſt her Care and Patience are doubled by her Affection? There are frequent Tragical Inſtances of Infants O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaid by Sleepy and Careleſs Nurſes, which much more rarely happen, where the Mother un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakes this Province her ſelf. Methinks then it is very reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able thus to argue, She is fitteſt to Nurſe the Child who loves it beſt; and if the Mother is not aſhamed to have it ſaid, That any Woman ſhould love her Child better than her ſelf, ſhe muſt be concluded fitteſt to Nurſe it; and ſhe ought to undertake that Office which requires ſo much Vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance and Patience, Care and Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, as can be expected only from the greateſt Love. Nothing is more common, than for Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenaries to let the poor Babe Cry
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:58129:36"/>it ſelf weary without regarding it, whilſt the Mothers Ears would have ſo affected her Heart, as to ſend her in all haſte to quiet it. The Mother ordinarily will ſpare no Pains to keep it Neat and Clean, whilſt Nurſes generally are ſo Negligent, that Naſtineſs oft breeds Diſeaſes, and the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Child <hi>Dirty,</hi> is a ſure Preludium of its Funeral, <hi>When Duſt is laid to Duſt, and Aſhes to Aſhes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§ 4. And here I cannot forbear to tranſlate a paſſage out of a learned Phyſician, Dr. <hi>Walter Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rys,</hi> in his Tract <hi>De acutis Morbis Infantum,</hi> viz. <q>That a worthy Divine, the Rector of <hi>Hayes,</hi> about twelve Miles from <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> with great Grief told him, that his Pariſh (being large and populous, and ſcituate in a very wholſome Air) at his firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thither was repleniſhed with Infants ſent abroad to be Nurſed; yet in the compaſs of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:58129:37"/>one Year he had buried them all except two: And that the ſame number of Nurſeries being again twice ſupplied (through the Mercenary Diligence of thoſe Women) out of <hi>London,</hi> he had again <hi>this ſame Year</hi> laid them all in their Graves before their time.</q>
                  <note place="margin">A. D. 1689.</note> So that by this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, the Citizens ſeem to put out their Children, not ſo properly to be <hi>Nurſed</hi> as to be <hi>Murdered.</hi> And I ſee not how they can be thought to have a due regard of their Childrens Lives, who after ſuch fair warning given them by a Phyſician that Practiſes among them, and ſeems peculiarly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd for the good of Infants, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve ſtill to run this Hazard, and prefer their own Eaſe before their Childrens Life.</p>
               <p>§ 5. But if the Child nurſed by a Stranger be not killed by her neglect, yet ſecondly it may be very much injured in its Health by <hi>the unſuitable Nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:58129:37"/>which it derives from her Breaſts.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Galen. de ſanit. tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end. <hi>l. 1. c. 7.</hi> Avicen l. 1. Fen. <hi>3.</hi> Senner. de curat. inf. <hi>part 1. c. 1.</hi>
                  </note> It is agreed upon by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and modern Phyſicians, that the Nouriſhment which Infants receive in the Womb, is of the ſame Nature with the Milk, which, ſoon after the Birth, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture provides for it in the Breaſts. And it is another approved Rule among them, that a ſudden Alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of Diet is oft Fatal, always dangerous, eſpecially to the Infirm and ſuch as are unable to reſiſt any violent Impreſſions. If then we conſider the <hi>waxen Tenderneſs</hi> of Infants (to uſe <hi>Galen</hi>s Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on as well as Argument) and the Moiſture of their Conſtitution,<note place="margin">Galen. de temper. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> which makes them very ſuſcepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of new Impreſſions, we muſt conclude that a change of Diet immediately upon their Birth, is likely enough to have a dangerous Influence upon them. Now there is as great Variety in Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as Faces, and conſequently it will be as hard to find a Nurſe of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:58129:38"/>the ſame Temperament with the Mother, as endued with the ſame Features. So that the fatal Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of Strangers Nurſing, may be imputed not always to their Negligence, but ſometimes to the great difference in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Mother and the Nurſe. For <hi>Galen</hi> peremptorily concludes, That the Child which draws its own Mothers Breaſts, uſes not only <hi>the moſt accuſtomed, but alſo the moſt proper aliment for it:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Galen. de ſan. tuend.</hi> l. 1. c. 7. <hi>Avicen.</hi> l. 1. <hi>Fen.</hi> 3. c. 2.</note> And <hi>Avicenna,</hi> That this it can <hi>beſt digeſt,</hi> and <hi>therefore it is moſt convenient for it;</hi> ſo that if <hi>any Indiſpoſition ſeize on it, the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Breaſt is moſt conducive to its Cure.</hi> And it is moreover to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, That for the moſt part thoſe Mothers who decline this Office, are of a delicate and finer Mold, and Mercenary Nurſes are generally robuſt and of a courſer allay: And though the latter may be the more Healthful, yet her Milk may for that reaſon be the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:58129:38"/>leſs ſuitable to the Conſtitution of an Infant conceived and nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hitherto in a Body more Fine and Tender. Brown Bread may be ſtrong and wholſome Food, yet not fit to be preſcribed on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to an infirm and delicate Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, which hath been long inured to Gruels and Pannado's. And if ſuch unſuitable Diet oft prove Fatal to the Adult, there is more reaſon to fear, leſt it never prove otherwiſe to Tender In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants.</p>
               <p>§ 6. But the Danger is much greater, <hi>Leſt Mercenary Nurſes tranſmit ſome deſperate Contagion into their Nurſeries.</hi> The Mothers Diſtemper is the moſt plauſible Pretence for her declining of this Office: And all conclude it very reaſonable, that in that caſe ſhe forbear to Nurſe, leſt her Infant Suck Death from her Breaſts whoſe Womb gave it Life, and ſhe propagate her Diſeaſes to it, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with her Milk, impregnated
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:58129:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>with the vicious Qualities of her Blood. But then the Argument is as ſtrong to oblige an Healthful Mother to Nurſe, leaſt ſhe ſhould commit it to a Mercenary, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with ſome latent Diſeaſe. The Right Reverend Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> in his Letters aſſures us,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net</hi>'s Let. 4 p. 248.</note> That one Mr. <hi>Gody</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of St. <hi>Gervais</hi> in <hi>Geneva,</hi> had a Daughter then ſixteen Years old, who having a Nurſe extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary thick of Hearing, ſpake all the little words that Children do at a Year old, but was Deaf at two years old. Which he concludes was cauſed by ſome Vapor the Nurſes Milk was charged with, which was propagated to the Child, when ſhe began to Suck more ſtrongly, and to take greater quantities of that corrupted Nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment. But this (though a very unhappy Infirmity) is very toler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, in compariſon of what other Infants have by this means been infected with. For there is a Story
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:58129:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>in Dr. <hi>Ambr. Parey,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Par. de Lue Ven. <hi>c. 2.</hi>
                  </note> a Famous French Chyrurgion, to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, ſo remarkable, that I cannot but judge it worthy to be tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed.</p>
               <p>§ 7. <q>A certain very good Citizen of this City of <hi>Paris,</hi> granted to his Wife, being a very Chaſt Woman, that condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally ſhe would Nurſe her own Child (of which ſhe was lately delivered) ſhe ſhould have a Nurſe in the Houſe to eaſe her of ſome part of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. By ill-hap the Nurſe they took was troubled with the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nereal Diſeaſe, wherewith ſhe Preſently infected the Child, the Child the Mother, the Mother her Husband, and he two of his Children, who frequently ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied him at Bed and Board, being ignorant of that Malignity wherewith he was inwardly tainted. In the mean while the Mother, when ſhe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved that her Nurſe-Child
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:58129:40"/>came not forward, but cried al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt perpetually, ſhe asked my Counſel to tell her the cauſe of the Diſeaſe, which was not hard to be done, for the whole Body thereof was repleniſhed with Venereal Scabs and Puſtles, the hired Nurſe and the Mothers Nipples were eaten in with vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulent Ulcers: Alſo the Fathers and the two other Childrens Bodies (whereof the one was three and the other four Years old) were troubled with the like Puſtles and Scabs. I told them that they had all the <hi>Lues Venerea,</hi> which took <hi>its Original and firſt Off-ſpring by malign Contagion from the hired Nurſe.</hi> I had them in Cure, and by Gods help healed them all except the Sucking Child, which died in the Cure. But the hired Nurſe was ſoundly laſhed in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and ſhould have been whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped through all the Streets of the City, but that the Magiſtrate
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:58129:40"/>had a Care to preſerve the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of the Unfortunate Family.</q>
               </p>
               <p>§ 8. Now if it be conſidered how common this Diſeaſe is in our Debauched Age, we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clued it is only to be imputed to the Secrecy of Phyſicians and Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgions, that we have not freſher Inſtances of this Nature. And this will be ſufficient to caution all Mothers that are Healthful, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than run the hazard of ſuch a Misfortune, to undergo the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigue of Nurſing themſelves. And thus you ſee how many ways a Mercenary Nurſe endangers the Life and Health of your Children. And if it be an antedated Murder, by cauſing Abortion to hinder the Propagation of a Man, it cannot be a leſs Crime, after he is born and regiſtred among Chriſtians, to ſuffer him to die, and contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute any of theſe ways to his Murder.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:58129:41"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Wherein are ſhewed the Miſchiefs which may be propagated from Mercenary Nurſes to the <hi>Minds</hi> of Children.</head>
               <p>§ 1. HAving in the former Chapter ſhewed what Harm a Child may receive in its Body by an hired Nurſe, I come in this to repreſent the <hi>Ill Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences ſuch an one may have on the Mind of her Nurſery.</hi> And this (Ladies) will deſerve your more Serious Conſideration, by how much the Soul of your Child is better than its Body; eſpecially ſince by the Improvements or Mis-improvements of the Mind, Perſons of Quality become extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Uſeful or Pernicious. Remernber it's not a Plow-man, but a Nobleman or a Gentleman, that may be ſpoiled, and that two ways, Either by the Diminution
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:58129:41"/>of the Childs Parts, or the Depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of his Diſpoſition or his Manners.</p>
               <p>§ 2. Firſt, <hi>The Nouriſhment re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from the Breaſts of a Merce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Nurſe, may debaſe the Spirit, and diminiſh the Parts of a Child.</hi> The Faculties of the Humane Soul in their Operations, depend very much upon the Diſpoſition of the Body in its united State. If then the Temper of the Body may be altered by Diet, the Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of the Mind may thereby be improved or impaired. Be the Hand never ſo Skillful, the Muſick will not be equally Melodious, when it ſtrikes on a bad, as on a good Inſtrument. <hi>David</hi> himſelf, ſaith one, could not have charmed <hi>Saul</hi>'s Melancholly Spirit with the Strings of his Bow,<note place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Taylour</hi>'s Grand Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. p. 22.</note> or the Wood of his Spear, as he did with his Harp. If the Soul of a Night<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingal were in the Body of an Owl, its Harmonious Warbling would be changed into hideous Screak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:58129:42"/>Or if the Humane Soul ſhould, according to the Fancy of <hi>Apulei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> be lodged in the Body of an Aſs, it would not be able to ſpeak or argue rationally, as it doth in the Body of a Philoſopher, being condemned to an Inſtrument not tuned for ſuch noble Harmony. Now whatever Temperament of Body a Child hath received from the Mother, if it be depraved by the Nurſe, that Alteration may deprave its Parts, and hugely im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair the Operations of its Mind. And when a Sucking Child draws its Nouriſhment longer from the Body of a ſtupid Nurſe, than it did, whilſt an Embrio, from the Subſtance of an ingenious Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, there is great reaſon to fear, leaſt that have a greater Influence in forming its Conſtitution than this; eſpecially happening whilſt it is Young and Tender, and very ſuſceptible of new Impreſſions.</p>
               <p>§ 3.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cauſ.</hi> Holy Court. l. 1. § 8. p. 29.</note> 
                  <hi>Cauſin</hi> tells us, That in the Hiſtory of <hi>Germany</hi> there is a
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:58129:42"/>Story of a Child taken in a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and preſented to the Landt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave of <hi>Heſſe,</hi> which having been bred among Wolves, learn'd to go on four feet, to Hunt, divide the Prey, and ſleep with them, and was in every thing, but his ſhape, become a perfect Wolf. And may not Ferity and Stupidity be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from the Breaſts of Brutiſh Women, as well as from Wolves, which if any look upon the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding Relation as a Fable rather than an Hiſtory, may paſs for the Moral of it.</p>
               <p>§ 4. I acknowledge the great Parts and brave Souls of many young Gentlemen, who have run an Hazard in drawing their firſt Nouriſhment from ſtrange Nurſes. But it may be theſe fell into the hands of ſome, whoſe Parts and Spirits were above their Fortune: Or perhaps though their Parts be great, yet they might have been more Conſiderable, had they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed the ſame Advantages at the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:58129:43"/>Breaſt as in the Womb. And any Diminution of their Parts, as well as the total loſs of them, is to be deplored; and whatever hath any probable Tendency thereto a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided. Beſides there are ſome In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Children in great Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies falling infinitely ſhort of their Parents Ingenuity, and every Mother may reaſonably fear, leaſt hers prove another of them, if ſhe venture on this Method for their Education, which in frequent In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances proves Pernicious. It is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported of <hi>Alcibiades,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plut. in Alcib.</note> whoſe Parts were advanced ſo far above the ordinary pitch of his Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that he drew his firſt Nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment from the Breaſts of a <hi>Spartan</hi> Woman.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id.</hi> in Lycur.</note> And the brave Spirits of thoſe Dames made other <hi>Grecians</hi> ambitious to purchaſe Nurſes from <hi>Sparta</hi> for the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of their Childrens Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. I leave it therefore, Ladies, to your Conſideration, whether it be ſafe to ſuffer your Children to Suck
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:58129:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Breaſts of any Woman leſs In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious than your ſelves, much leſs ſuch ſtupid Women, as in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Parts and Spirits you would be very loath to have them reſemble, leaſt your generous Plants ſet in a barren and canker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Soil, degenerate and become Unfruitful.</p>
               <p>§ 5. But Secondly, It ought further to be conſidered, <hi>Whether the Suck of a Mercenary Nurſe may not corrupt the Diſpoſition of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants Soul, and depràve its Manners.</hi> For whoſoever impartially conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders it, will find great reaſon to fear, leaſt the Child imbibe the Nurſes ill Conditions, together with her Milk. Though Vertue is a Supernatural Perfection, added to our Nature in this State of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pravation by the Influences of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Grace, yet ſome Inclinations to it may be owing to the Temper of the Body, and propagated by a Communication of Spirits in the Nouriſhment. Much more may
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:58129:44"/>Vicious Diſpoſitions, which are Natural, and depend more upon the Temper of the Blood and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. The Peeviſhneſs, the Luſt, the Pride, the Stubbornneſs or Baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a Nurſe, receive great En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement from the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her Body, which being in ſome meaſure propagated to her Nurſery, gives it alſo a great and Unhappy Propenſity to the ſame Vices. This ſo far prevailed with the Mother of St. <hi>Bernard,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Guil. Abb. in vit. Bern. <hi>l. 1. c. 1.</hi>
                  </note> that ſhe would not let her Son draw any Breaſts but her own, leaſt he ſhould draw from them ſome Contagion of Vice. And the common Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, which expreſſes an Invete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Habit of Vice, <hi>By drinking it in with the Mothers Milk,</hi> being grounded on univerſal Conſent, gives great Authority to this No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>§ 6. And <hi>Dion Caſſius</hi> gives this account of the Prodigious Cruelty of <hi>Caligula,</hi> who was the Son of the Famous <hi>Germanicus</hi> and <hi>Agrippina</hi>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:58129:44"/>the Daughter of <hi>M. Agrippa,</hi> two as Vertuous and Generous Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as Heathen <hi>Rome</hi> could boaſt of. That to the end he might be of a Martial Diſpoſition, they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted him to a <hi>Maſculine Nurſe,</hi> one that was Hairy on the Face like a Man, drew the long Bow, run at the Ring, managed the great Horſe, and was in all things moſt Cruelly and Miſchievouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined. And from ſuch a Nurſe he became ſo in love with Blood, that he not only delighted to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at the Execution of Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, but would lick the very Blood of the Weapons wherewith they were executed. And <hi>Tiberius,</hi> who was ſuch a Monſter for Leachery, is ſaid to have been Nurſed by one no leſs famous for Unchaſtity than the other for Cruelty. And I knew a Gentleman, who had been very Sandalous in his Life for Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and confeſſed in my preſence, that his firſt Debauch was at Fourteen, with and through the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:58129:45"/>Enticements of his Luſtful Nurſe. Who would not think his Parents to blame, for turning him off to ſuch a Monſter? Since from his Mother perhaps he might have Sucked a more Happy Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſhe being a very Chaſt and Vertuous Woman.</p>
               <p>§ 7. Conſider then, Ladies, what Aſſurance you have, that the Mercenary Nurſe is not of a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Diſpoſition, and conclude it your Duty, not to put off your Child to any other, unleſs one from whom it may imbibe better Qualities than from your ſelves. And ſince few of thoſe Nicer Dames, who decline this Office, think better of others than of themſelves, I hope they will not be ſo unkind, as to venture their Children abroad, where they may be likely to draw in a Diſpoſition to thoſe Vices which they moſt abhor. I am much inclined to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to the Opinion of Wiſe <hi>Cato,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plut. in Catone.</note> That for the moſt part <hi>Noble Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:58129:45"/>are endued with more Vertuous Inclinations than the meaner ſort.</hi> And methinks for that reaſon they ought not to place out their Children with any Women of baſer Allay, and leſs Vertuous Diſpoſitions.</p>
               <p>§ 8. And thus I have given you an account of the probable Miſchievous Conſequences of Nurſing Children abroad, which are ſufficient to perſuade all that truly love their Family, or their Children, to forego that unjuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiable Cuſtom. Unjuſtifiable I ſay, for I am ſure none can juſtifie themſelves either in point of Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence or Duty, if they ſtill adhere to it. And this leads me to the laſt part of my undertaking, which ſhall be the ſubject of the next Chapter, The Inſufficiency of the common Excuſes alledged by thoſe that decline the Nurſing of their own Children.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:58129:46"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> In which are mentioned the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Plea's</hi> for Nurſing Children abroad: Together with the Inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency of them, and the true Cauſes thereof are repreſented.</head>
               <p>§ 1. I Come now in the laſt place to remonſtrare, that the Cauſes for which the generality of thoſe Mothers, that are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and able, refuſe to Nurſe, are ſo far from excuſing, that they more evidently demonſtrate and aggravate to their Fault in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. For whatever Plea's are fram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for them, they may be reſolved into ſome of theſe three Sins, Luxury, Covetouſneſs or Pride.</p>
               <p>§ 2. Firſt, Some of them pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from and convince them of <hi>Luxury.</hi> For hitherto it is reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to reduce the pretended Fears of diminiſhing their Beauty, and prejudicing their Health by the diſturbance of their Reſt, and
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:58129:46"/>other Toils incident to the Care of an helpleſs Infant. For I dare appeal to any one, who imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally conſiders it, whether any thing but Luxury dictates this Pretence. For firſt, There is neither <hi>Reaſon nor Experience</hi> on their ſide, who pretend Nurſing to be the Decay of a Womans Health or Beauty. The contrary is generally obſerved, That it helps the Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite and Digeſtion, which is more likely to preſerve both, than de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy either.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Morton Phthiſiol.</hi> l. 1. c. 7.</note> I find it confirmed by the Experience of Learned Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, that oft Conſumptive Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons have been cured by Nurſing their Children; and ſuch as at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times have looked Meagre and Pale, whilſt they have Nurſed have been Plump, Fleſhy, and of a vivid Complexion. Whereas on the other hand, in drying their Breaſts, Women very commonly run apparent Hazards of deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not their Health only but their Lives. The unnatural ſtopping up
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:58129:47"/>of theſe Fountains, occaſions the corrupting of the Milk, and that corrupted Milk infecting the Blood, oft raiſes ſuch a Ferment as produces a Fevor, or ſome other Fatal Diſtemper. And none can think it Prudence to throw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into immature Death to avoid Wrinkles.</p>
               <p>§ 3. Again Secondly, Granting that the Nurſing of half a dozen Children ſhould decay the Glory of the Face a Year or two ſooner, <hi>How could Beauty be better beſtowed, than in ſuch a Work of Piety toward her own Family and Poſterity?</hi> Nor do I ſee how thoſe Ladies can juſtifie themſelves againſt the Charge of Vanity and Luxury, who prefer the colour of their own Face before the advancing of ſuch important Intereſts. Did you ever ſee a vain Fop ſo enſlaved to his neat Cloaths, that he declined Buſineſs moſt proper and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, for fear of ſome little ſpot fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on them, or any rude Motion
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:58129:47"/>to diſorder his Garniture? There is as much Vanity in being a Slave to a fair Skin, as to a gawdy Suit. The miraculous Beauty of <hi>Sarah</hi> in her old Age, and of the Bleſſed Virgin in Youth, were neither ſo overvalued, as to deter them from being Nurſes. So that thoſe may be concluded to value too highly the Smoothneſs and Superficial Glory of their Skin, who prefer it before the greateſt Good of their Poſterity.</p>
               <p>§ 4. And Thirdly, For ſuch as decline Nurſing, <hi>For fear of having their Reſt diſturbed, or being other ways overloaded,</hi> there needs no other Argument than their own Apology, to convince them of <hi>Soft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Luxury.</hi> For what would any one judge of a Mother, whom he ſhould hear wiſhing that ſome one could undergo the Sickneſſes attending her Conception, the Toil of bearing her Child in the Womb, and the Throes of Travel in her ſtead? Would he not conclude,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:58129:48"/>That ſuch an one had deeply im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bibed the Counſel, which <hi>Epicurus</hi> is ſaid ſomewhere by <hi>Arrian</hi> to have given his Scholars, to enjoy <hi>the Pleaſures of Marriage,</hi> but by <hi>all means avoid the trouble of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</hi> Now if ſuch a Wiſh argue too much Senſuality, How can they avoid that Imputation, who by throwing off as much of the Pains of a Mother as they can, make it apparent, that it is only from the Neceſſity of Nature that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline no more? One that turns off her Child to be Nurſed by a Stranger, for fear of taking Pains with it by Day, or being diſturbed by it in the Night, evidences there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, that ſhe carried it in the Womb Forty Weeks, and underwent the Pangs of Child-birth, only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Nature in thoſe caſes could not admit of a Subſtitute. There is no Vertue in enduring thoſe Pains for your Child which you cannot avoid: And there are ſome Pains God hath ſo contrived,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:58129:48"/>that they may be avoided (theſe I mean that attend the Nurſing of it) that by a voluntary undertaking of them, you may make it appear how little you value your Eaſe, when it ſtands in Competition with your Duty. For doubtleſs ſhe loves her Eaſe too well, who will not undergo thoſe Labours for her own Child, which he expects another ſhould take for Wages. Our Holy Religion, as it requires the great eſt Charity in all its Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, ſo it preſcribes <hi>Labours of Love;</hi> and conſequently allows not of that over-great Tenderneſs to our ſelves, which is inconſiſtent with a <hi>Laborious Charity;</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to the moſt natural and near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Objects of a Mothers Charity, her own Children.</p>
               <p>§ 5. Laſtly, <hi>The Pretence of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ability to Nurſe, is oft reducible to this Head of Luxury.</hi> It is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Plea of thoſe Mothers, who put their Children out to Nurſe, that either they <hi>want Nipples or
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:58129:49"/>Milk:</hi> And though this may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the caſe of ſome few, yet I am perſuaded, not of all that pretend it. Such dry Breaſts, as one obſerves, are like the Gout, which is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent among the Rich, but a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger among the Poor. Few of thoſe Women who are too Poor to hire a Nurſe, but they are able to Nurſe themſelves; and I make no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion but many of our Rich and Honourable Dames, who pretend to want Suck or Nipples, would have had both if their Fortunes had been leſſ. Now in all ſuch, Luxury is the real Motive, though a Natural Inability be the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence.<note n="*" place="margin">I might here add one Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular more reducible to this Head, which though many are aſhamed to plead, hath yet a great Influence on them in declining their Duty: I mean the <hi>Reſtraints</hi> that the Diſcharge of it would bring on them. They cannot Dreſs exactly according to the Mode, if to give Suck they muſt be called ſo oft to open their Breaſt: Nor will this be conſiſtent with the Liberty they take to Revel and Game oft till after Midnight. But if the bare Propoſal of this Plea do not convince and ſhame them that uſe it, I muſt deſpair of prevailing with them. But ſince I am ſure there cannot be a better Argument to this Duty, than that it may be a means to reſtrain them from thoſe Faults, I will not Deſpair.</note>
               </p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:58129:49"/>
               <p>§ 6. But that thoſe Ladies, who have no better Plea's for the Neglect of this Duty, than theſe which ſo evidently convict them of Luxury, and too great a Fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their own Eaſe, will by a Serious Reflection upon this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, perſuade themſelves ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to diſcharge this Duty for the future toward their Children, than to expoſe themſelves to juſt Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, by ſuch Apologies for their Neglect. For (to conclude this firſt Cauſe) what is the true difference between a Modeſt Wife and an Adultreſs? But that the firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to bring forth a Child to the World, to be a Servant of God, a Citizen to the Commonwealth, and an Object for her Charity and Diligence; whilſt the latter aims at no more than the gratify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of her lend Inclinations and baſe Luſts. And I need not to ſay, how near thoſe Mothers come to this latter Character, who after the Conſummation of Marriage,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:58129:50"/>and the Birth of a Child (as if Luſt: were all they intended) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline the Labour and the Charity it gives them an opportunity to exerciſe towards it, and transfer them all upon another.</p>
               <p>§ 7. Secondly, There is another Plea uſed for the declining of this Office <hi>which is the reſult of Avarice,</hi> as the former is of <hi>Luxuryr,</hi> and made uſe of by the Trading part of the Nation, as thoſe by the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. The Nurſing of a Child is looked on as too great a Confine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Wife, who by her In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection over the Houſhold Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, or Attendance in the Shop, may ſave her Husband much more than the Hire of a Nurſe amounts to. But granting this, if (as hath been ſhewed) Nurſing be the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Duty, no proſpect of gaining by the neglect can ſuperſede her Obligation to it. And if I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Nature of Covetouſneſs, it is ſuch a Love of Gain as this, that draws one to the neglect of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:58129:50"/>any Obligation, which is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with his Profit. The Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is not, Whether it may be as Conducive to your Temporal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, but whether it be as Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with your Duty, to put out your Child to a Stranger, as to Nurſe it your ſelf. And if Avarice be excluded from the Conſult, you muſt conclude, that other buſineſs ought to give place to this, which is ſo properly the Buſineſs of a Mother. For unleſs you love your Child too little, and your Gain too nmch, you will be ſenſible, that if your Infant be ſpoiled, or ſuffer any Prejudice in Body or Mind, you can be no Gainers, though your Domeſtick Buſineſs, or your Shop ſhould be better attended.</p>
               <p>§ 8. Laſtly, I humbly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it to the Conſideration of all Mothers, eſpecially Perſons of Quality, whether by adhering to this unnatural Cuſtom, they do not ſhew themſelves <hi>Guilty of a great deal of Pride.</hi> You think it
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:58129:51"/>below you to ſtoop to the Office of a meaner Mother, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as a piece of State, and Pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctilio of Honour, turn off the Drudgery of Nurſing to another. For if this were not a very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing Motive, the <hi>Great and Honourable</hi> would not be ſo uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally conformable to this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable Cuſtom. But may they not as reaſonably conclude it too great a Condeſcention to become a Mother as a Nurſe? For there is the ſame equality between the moſt Honourable Lady and her Child, as between the meaneſt Beggar and hers; and there is no more reaſon why the beſt ſhould think Scorn to Nurſe her own at her Breaſt, than to bear it in her Womb. Let then thoſe whom God hath advanced into a Superior Rank in the World, learn to have Modeſt Thoughts of themſelves, and they will be aſhamed to let ſuch vain Punctilio's of Honour and Greatneſs influence them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:58129:51"/>Let ſuch remember that the Laws of God and Nature equally oblige the Lady as the Beggar, the City as the Country Dame; and they will reſolve not to plead the Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtick Privilege of their Quality, againſt the Good of their Children and their own Duty. God expects that the greateſt Lady, when ſhe becomes a Mother, ſhould do the Duties of a Mother; and ſhe cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly <hi>thinks of her ſelf more highly than ſhe ought to think,</hi> whoever is ſo Vain, as to fancy it below her to do her Duty. And if <hi>Luxury, Avarice</hi> and <hi>Pride,</hi> be the true Cauſes of this Cuſtoms univerſal Prevailence, whatever are the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, it muſt needs be concluded inexcuſably Sinful: Which was the laſt thing I undertook to prove.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:58129:52"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Concluſion.</hi> Wherein a Pathetick Addreſs is made to all, both Fathers and Mothers, that they will admit the preceding Particulars into their Serious and Impartial Conſideration.</head>
               <p>§ 1. IT only remains, that I wind up this Diſcourſe with a Serious Admonition to all thoſe whom God hath honoured with the Title of Parents, that they will allow it an Impartial Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>§ 2. And firſt I ſhall ſpeak to <hi>all Mothers,</hi> becauſe they are Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily and Principally concern'd. And methinks the very name might ſupercede the Repetition of all other Arguments. For what is the Import of a <hi>Mother?</hi> Why is the Earth ſtiled the common Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all things, but that it Nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes all that it produceth? And do not all other Beings the ſame, whether Animate or Inanimate?
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:58129:52"/>Do not Grapes hang on the Vine, and Fruits on the Trees that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced them, taking their Increaſe from the Sap of the Wood, to which they owe their Original? And among Animals, Doth not the Lamb know its own Dam, and run to her Dug among a Thouſand in the ſame Flock? Nay even Savage Lions and Bears ſtand tamely to be Sucked by their young Cubs. The Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher <hi>Favorinus</hi> was then in the right,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>A. Gell.</hi> l. 12. c. 1.</note> when he ſtiled her <hi>but half a Mother,</hi> who Nouriſhes in her Womb what ſhe knows not, and conſequently doth not yet love, but caſts it off as ſoon as ſhe knows it, and firſt begins to love it. Nay ſhe is not to be reputed ſo much as half a Mother, ſince the Nurſe doth longer communicate Conſtituent Nouriſhment to her Child from her Body in Twelve Months, than the Mother in Nine. And how, Ladies, would you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it, if your Child ſhould refuſe
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:58129:53"/>to call you <hi>Mother,</hi> or own any other Woman to be more its Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than you? If this would grieve or vex you, methinks you ſhould be aſham'd, that any other ſhould have done more of the Office of a Mother for it than your ſelf.</p>
               <p>§ 3. Next to your relation to your Child, let me <hi>remind you of your Religion,</hi> which recommends the greateſt Charity to Strangers and Enemies. And how can it be conſiſtent with your Profeſſion of Chriſtianity, which obliges you to love your Enemies, to be deſective in your Love to) our neareſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations? Look then, unkind Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, look on your poor Infant newly thruſt out of your Womb, how Helpleſs and Forlorn it is. Hear the Lamentations wherewith it begins the World. What are thoſe cries, but the beſt ways it hath to implore your Pity, ſolicite your further Care, and to beg of you, now that it is excluded from the Womb, to entertain it in your
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:58129:53"/>Boſom? Look on your own Breaſts, which ſoon after the. Birth ſpring full of Milk. Did Nature intend no more in this, but to put you to the trouble of drying them? Or did it deſign you ſhould ſupply your Babe from that Store which ſhe hath provided? It had been much more wiſely contrived, for you to have been without Breaſts and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacles for Milk, if now you have them repleniſhed, it will be the beſt to deprive your ſelves of them. Is it not then a bold Reflection on the Divine Wiſdom, to act as if you could have contrived the parts of your Bodies better than he hath done? If then you cannot be ſo far. forſaken of Reaſon, as to imagine that the Author of your Being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended your Breaſts only for need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Excreſſences, much leſs Snares and Temptations to your ſelves and others; as oft as you look on them remember their proper uſe; and reſolve not to ſuffer your Child to want what Nature hath enabled
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:58129:54"/>you to ſupply it with. It is now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved out of your Womb into your Arms, and the Meat which Nouriſhed it there, follows it to your Breaſts, that it may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by the Principles of its Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution. Let not thoſe parts then ſerve only to miniſter to Pride and Wantonneſs, which are ſo appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently intended by God for your Infants Suſtentation.</p>
               <p>§ 4. I acknowledge there are but very few Perſons of Quality that ſtoop to this Employment; but this ought not to diſcourage you from it, but rather confirm your Reſolution to undertake it, as it gives you an opportunity to ſhew your ſelves <hi>Singularly good Mothers.</hi> Piety is then truly Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ick, when it dare own a neglected Duty, and rather be <hi>laugh'd</hi> at, than <hi>deſerve</hi> to be <hi>reproved.</hi> And if Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom were a concluſive Argument in all caſes, there are very few Vices but might plead it as well as this. And your Husbands have
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:58129:54"/>as good a Plea for the Vices you moſt diſlike (ſuch as Drunkenneſs, keeping Miſſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) as you have for hiring other Women to Nurſe your Children. Thoſe Vices may plead Cuſtom among the Men, as this among the Women of Quality. Oppoſe then this evil Cuſtom a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Women by your Example, and make the Experiment, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you can hereby teach the Men, as well as your own Sex, to be aſhamed of wicked Faſhions. For who knows how much your Illuſtrious Example may contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to the overthrowing of Vile Cuſtoms, and the reſtoring of Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to neglected Duties.</p>
               <p>§ 5. In a word, Let me beſeech you to conſider, how ye can an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to God, your Families, or your Country, the Omiſſion of this Duty: If your ſlighting of Natures Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates occaſion any of the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Miſchiefs to the beſt Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies and greateſt Hopes of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for ſuch we may reckon the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:58129:55"/>Children of our Nobility and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try to be.</p>
               <p>§ 6. Eſpecially, Let me intreat you once more to conſider, how many Children this Cuſtom Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders every Year, and what <hi>an Hue and Cry</hi> of Innocents Blood there is againſt it, which may well over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the Abetters of it writh Divine Vengeance. Murder is an Horrid Crime, but Parricide is worſe. We deteſt the Wickedneſs, and Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty of a poor Wretch, who to hide her Shame ſtrangles her Baſtard. And how much better are thoſe Mothers, who without ſo great a Temptation (only to gratifie their Luxury or Eaſe) reſign up their Children, the hopes of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily and the Nation, to the Slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? If there were as much Natural Affection among <hi>our Nicer Dames,</hi> as once there was in the <hi>Mothers of Bethlehem,</hi> there would be as many <hi>Rachels</hi> among them Weeping for the Slaughter of their Innocent Babes. Eſpecially ſince not a Cruel
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:58129:55"/>
                  <hi>Herod</hi> is the <hi>Tyrant</hi> and <hi>Aſſaſſinate,</hi> but themſelves. Nor is this any Vain, much leſs Uncharitable Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, ſince it is obvious to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Obſervation, that though thoſe Mothers who do not Nurſe, generally bring forth more Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren yet; fewer of them arrive to Maturity and ſurvive them; which cannot be imputed ſo much to the Frequency of Production ſince they are uſually brought forth as ſtrong and lively as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) as to the ill Nurſing of them by Strangers. And if we juſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt their Inhumane Idolatry, who offered up their Children in the Fiery Embraces of <hi>Moloch</hi> (ſince it is no more excuſable to make ſuch Sacrifices to Luxury than to Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition) methinks it ſhould be a very Melancholly Conſideration to all Mothers, that the Lives of many Thouſand poor Innocents, even in this one Nation, are Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed every Year for the Support of this Luxurious and Unnatural Cuſtom.</p>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:58129:56"/>
               <p>§ 7. But I muſt confeſs there is one Caſe very neceſſary to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, which hath not yet been mentioned, viz. <hi>That very oft the Father is unwilling that his Wife ſhould undertake this Office.</hi> And if he will not conſent to her Nurſing, how can ſhe do the Duty of a Wife, unleſs ſhe wave this Office of a Mother? In anſwer to this I have this only to return, That all I have hitherto aimed at in this Diſcourſe, is to perſuade Mothers to be willing to Nurſe their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: If this be effected, all I have to add is, That if any Husband be Obſtinate in refuſing to permit it, the Wifes Duty is, to be obedient to him, and leave him to anſwer for the Neglect which ſhe cannot help. But that this may not here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after be any ones Caſe, I ſhall put an end to this Tract,</p>
               <p>§ 8. Secondly, By an earneſt Addreſs <hi>to all Fathers,</hi> that they do not put their Wives upon ſuch an Unhappy Strait by their Perverſe
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:58129:56"/>Obſtinacy, but rather (as becomes their Duty) encourage them to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake and aſſiſt them all they can in performing this Office. You have, Sirs, an equal Concern with your Wives in all the precedent Arguments. If the Word of God and the Law of Nature oblige them to Nurſe, it obliges you to teach them their Duty, or at leaſt to encourage them to practiſe it, and not hinder them from it. And whatever Miſchiefs redound to your Family, or your Child, by drawing the Breaſt of a Stranger, they equally concern you as her, and (unleſs you have put off Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, together with Humanity and Natural Affection) muſt produce in you a very Senſible Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. So that you are as much obliged to prevent them as ſhe, and all the Guilt is juſtly to be laid at your door, if it happen through your means that ſhe doth not. Moſt of the Pains and Toil of Nurſing is hers, and if your Reſt
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:58129:57"/>be ſometimes broken, you are very Soft and Luxurious indeed, if you grudge to endure much more than that for your Childs good. Nay you are very Churliſh and Unkind to her, if you contribute not all you can to make her Duty as eaſie as may be to her. <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s Joy at the Weaning of his Son,<note place="margin">Gen. 21.8.</note> is an Evidence he was well pleaſed that <hi>Sarah</hi> had Nurſed him. And <hi>Elkanah,</hi> Who before obliged his Wives conſtantly to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany him to the Tabernacle, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily conſents to <hi>Hannahs</hi> ſtay at home for the Nurſing of her Son.<note place="margin">1 Sam. 1.23.</note> No ſooner doth ſhe move it, but he anſwers, <hi>Do as ſeemeth thee good.</hi> And if all Husbands were in this like <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Elkanah,</hi> the moſt Wives would be like <hi>Sarah</hi> and <hi>Hannah,</hi> as ready, I mean, to Nurſe as they. It is very rare that any Wife refuſes this Office, when her Husband is deſirous ſhe would undertake it; much more when he perſuades and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:58129:57"/>her, by the Proviſion of all convenient Helps and Aſſiſtance for her.</p>
               <p>§ 9. In a word, A Cuſtom ſo inveterate as this is, will not be ſo effectually broke, as by a Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Concurrence of both the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> and the <hi>Mother.</hi> If the Mother be deſirous to Nurſe, few Fathers will be ſo Moroſe and Unnatural as to refuſe their Conſent: Or if the Father be Solicitous that the Mother her ſelf ſhould do this Office for his Son, there are not many Women ſo in love with their own Eaſe, or forgetful of their Childrens Advantage, as to decline it. But where both de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it, they will be Meet-helps indeed, and afford ſuch mutual Encouragement, as Mill make all the Fatigues of it Eaſie and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful. And Delightful, I dare undertake, it will be to both, if there be in them the leaſt Spark of Good Nature. There is ſuch a Faſcination in the Innocent
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:58129:58"/>Poſtures, and Gradual Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of Reaſon, the pretty Smiles and confuſed Jargon, the calm Endearments and unfeigned Love of theſe little Innocents, that the Wiſeſt Men have found a Satisfactory Diverſion in their Company. And if any one que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions this, let him forbear to Cenſure, till he have made trial of this Pleaſure of a Father: As <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> once anſwered one,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aelian. var. Hiſt.</hi> l. 12. c. 15.</note> who laughed at him for condeſcending to Play with his Son. For I have known ſome Fathers at firſt very Averſe to their Wives Nurſing, who after Experience of thoſe Pleaſing Diverſions, that are to be found in the conſtant Company of a little Babe, would not on any Terms loſe the Repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of that Pleaſure, by turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the next abroad to a Strange Nurſe.</p>
               <p>§ 10. Thus have I finiſhed my Undertaking, and doubt not but I have ſaid enough to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:58129:58"/>my Sincere Compaſſion for the Expoſed Infants of Great and Honourable Parents; enough to vindicate thoſe few Mothers, who by performing this Office themſelves, have provoked the Scoffs of the reſt; and enough to diſcharge mine own Duty in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minding them of theirs, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my ſlender Ability; which were all the ends I could propoſe to my ſelf, with any Aſſurance of Succeſs. But if the Divine Bleſſing make theſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers more Succeſsful, if it ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect theſe few ſmall Stones, taken out of a Shepherds Scrip, as to Foil a Gigantick Inveterate Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, and prevail on any, though never ſo few Ladies, to become Nurſes, I ſhall hope for a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Victory from <hi>their Example,</hi> which I cannot from my <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</hi> Let but a few more truly Generous and Noble Matrons, come in and joyn with thoſe few that have already begun to ſet
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:58129:59"/>this Age a good Example; and ſuch a bright Conſtellation can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be took notice of, and have a vigorous Influence to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it as Faſhionable for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for Ladies to Diſcharge this their Duty, as it is at preſent to Neglect it.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>FAmily Devotions for Sunday Evenings. In Two Volumes: Each containing Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Practical Diſcourſes, with ſo many Prayers for two Quarters of the Year. By <hi>Theophilus Dorrington.</hi> Printed for <hi>John Wyat</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:58129:59"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
